<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nathan Oseroff on Nathan Oseroff</title>
    <link>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Nathan Oseroff on Nathan Oseroff</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Nathan Oseroff</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Clarifying three philosophic myths surrounding objections to demarcation criteria</title>
      <link>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/publication/popper/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/publication/popper/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Almost Everyone Misunderstands The Problem(s) of Demarcation</title>
      <link>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/talk/almosteveryonemisunderstands/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/talk/almosteveryonemisunderstands/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A return to demarcation</title>
      <link>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/publication/areturntodemarcation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/publication/areturntodemarcation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the Pillars</title>
      <link>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/publication/beyondthepillars/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/publication/beyondthepillars/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epistemic counter-closure confronts the success of miasma theory</title>
      <link>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/publication/counterclosure/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/publication/counterclosure/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One approach to escaping the pragmatic problem of induction: sailing between Scylla and Charybdis</title>
      <link>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/publication/salmon/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/publication/salmon/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Carnap&#39;s motivations for demarcation</title>
      <link>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/post/carnapdemarcation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/post/carnapdemarcation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
It&#39;s appropriate that any criticisms of a position accurately reflect the position that has been advanced, rather than a pale imitation of the real thing.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Following this rather pablum observation that criticism must aim true, in this post, I set out what I think is a brief but fair reconstruction from some of my notes of a number of Carnap&#39;s motivations for his demarcationist programme. I then provide a short assessment of the Carnapian programme, cutting off at the legs two objections unfairly raised against it: (1) Carnap&#39;s criteria are self-refuting, for they are neither empirically meaningful nor analytic; (2) the criteria are parasitic on the analytic/synthetic distinction, and this distinction cannot be maintained.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In a later post, I&#39;ll show how the unstated differences between Carnap and Popper in the relatively neglected Carnap/Popper dispute is a core and open question in the demarcationist project, namely both Carnap and Popper present to different attempts at answering the question of what &lt;i&gt;function&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;demarcation criteria should serve.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Since I&#39;m not a Carnap scholar, though, I&#39;d like to preface my notes by making it clear that any corrections in my exegesis on Carnap are appreciated.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
1. The decline and fall of logical empiricism&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
There is a story told within philosophical circles that follows a certain structure:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
First: the logical empiricists concerned themselves with a problem, which we can call the &lt;i&gt;demarcation problem&lt;/i&gt;. This problem was to set out the differences between empirically meaningful from empirically meaningless sentences.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Second: intractable problems with these early formulations of criteria lead to more mature solutions to the problem of demarcation. These later solutions to this problem were best articulated in the writings of two Austrian philosophers, Rudolf Carnap and Sir Karl Popper (as well as the English philosopher A.J. Ayer). Carnap and Popper each proposed different solutions to the problem of demarcation--certain necessary and sufficient conditions--and engaged in a minor philosophical dispute over their respective criteria.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Third: this dispute, as well as the entire demarcationist project, was mooted due to a number of arguments from philosophers like W.V.O. Quine and Carl Hempel (1950), which showed, in part, that this distinction was parasitic on the analytic/synthetic distinction, and the analytic/synthetic distinction could not be maintained. Other criticisms focused on other apparent problems, such as the purported self-refuting nature of the demarcation criteria: the proposed demarcation criteria were themselves not analytic nor empirically meaningful, and therefore were categorised as empirically meaningless.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Following Church&#39;s (1949) devastating criticism of Ayer&#39;s (1946) criterion of demarcation, this lead to, as Soames (2003, 291) concludes, ?the end of attempts to formulate the empiricist criterion? A few attempts were made to reformulate Ayer&#39;s criterion to save it from objections? However, none proved successful.?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Fifth: Hempel lamented in 1951, ?It now seems that this type of approach offers little hope for the attainment of precise criteria? (1951, 64). After these mounting problems had accumulated, this distinction between empirically meaningful and empirically meaningless sentences could no longer stand, and collapsed like a house of cards. Consequently, there could be no solution to the demarcation problem.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
In sum, the demarcationist project progressed through the stages of (i) an immature research programme, (ii) a mature research programme, (iii) a regressive research programme faced with overwhelmingly strong criticisms, (iv) finally, a defunct research programme. Demarcationism died from a thousand cuts on all fronts, and was buried forever.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
In what follows, I briefly explain how this story does not bear much resemblance to the facts, specifically examining the second point: &lt;i&gt;the supposed minor dispute between Carnap and Popper&lt;/i&gt;. While there &lt;i&gt;was&lt;/i&gt; a dispute over whether to prefer Carnap or Popper&#39;s proposed demarcation criteria, there is a far greater, and far more interesting dispute that has been overlooked, and reframes much of the criticism raised against Carnap and Popper: both have fundamentally different &lt;i&gt;motivations&lt;/i&gt; for adopting demarcation criteria that remain unchallenged by criticisms of their respective demarcation criteria, and exist unstated in the background of their dispute. Furthermore, these motivations remain unchallenged in the face of criticism from Quine and other critics. In fact, by understanding their motivations, we see that a number of objections to Carnap and Popper&#39;s respective criteria are misdirected.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Their disagreements over their motivations for formulating the demarcation problem can be understood as a metaphilosophical problem that is implicit in their motivations for accepting either of their formulations: we have the choice to frame the demarcation problem and solutions to demarcation as Carnap did, and frame them in ways that consequently &lt;i&gt;deflate&lt;/i&gt; traditional philosophical discourse to be merely talk about different forms of talking (and nothing more) . This roughly tracks the general empiricist attitude to traditional metaphysics. Or we can choose to frame the demarcation problem and solutions to demarcation as Popper did--more &lt;i&gt;neutrally&lt;/i&gt;--to treat traditional philosophical discourse as not &lt;i&gt;necessarily&lt;/i&gt; deflated if demarcation criteria were available. This roughly tracks the motivations seen in Kant&#39;s critical philosophy. Both these approaches to traditional philosophy survive intact.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
2. Why focus on Carnap and Popper?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: start;&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br style=&#34;text-align: start;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Unpacking the thesis that there is some important &lt;i&gt;prima facie&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;distinction to be found in our ways of speaking (e.g. analytic/synthetic, a priori/a posteriori, necessary/contingent, empirically significant/empirically non-significant), we can see that one could argue for this demarcation criterion in one of two ways, one which we can call ?Carnapian? and the other ?Popperian?, and for purposes that are at odds with one another.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Furthermore, it is also worth examining their respective metaphilosophical approaches because it helps clear the air over the internal disagreements between demarcationists, as well as where their demarcation criteria may, on occasion, be reconciled without any deleterious effects to their metaphilosophical aims.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Lastly, comparing Carnap and Popper&#39;s views on the role of the demarcation criterion in a systematic way, as well as their respective proposals, helps clarify exegetical issues in reading Carnap and Popper if we are interested in giving a fair reading to philosophical positions, for it is oftentimes not clear what their respective motivations and criteria are when first reading their work: Carnap and Popper, although at times antagonistic towards one another&#39;s metaphilosophical views of the purpose of demarcation criteria (cf. Popper 1962a,&amp;nbsp;and&amp;nbsp;Carnap 1936), intentionally downplay their influences on one another on more mundane matters and over-emphasise their philosophical differences (e.g. Popper 1962a).&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
3. Possible purposes of demarcation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
In coming to understand this metaphilosophical dispute, it is better to begin with a question about the role, function or purpose of different kinds of sentences: what &lt;i&gt;functional&lt;/i&gt; purpose, in the broadest strokes imaginable, would any demarcation criterion serve?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
There is the intuitive idea that demarcation criteria serve the function of separating &lt;i&gt;different ways of speaking&lt;/i&gt;: some sentences are analytic, others synthetic; some sentences are a priori, others a posteriori; and so on. Some &lt;i&gt;speech-acts&lt;/i&gt; seek to be&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;empirically informative&lt;/i&gt; and others fall short: they are&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;empirically uninformative&lt;/i&gt;. These ways of carving up our language do not fully map on to one another, but our focus begins with the distinction between empirically informative and empirically uninformative speech-acts.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
This way of approaching the demarcation problem of the logical empiricists is imperfectly analogous to H.P. Grice&#39;s conversational maxim of quantity: one&#39;s speech must be &lt;i&gt;informative&lt;/i&gt;. A violation of a conversational norm may give no information, even though--and this is key here--the corresponding sentence may be synthetic.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
For example, consider the synthetic sentence, &#39;For every person, upon their birth, there exist a immaterial, invisible guardian angel that follows them throughout their life, subtly guiding them towards desirable ends and away from undesirable ends&#39;. The sentence appears to say a great deal (the existence of guardian angels), is synthetic and truth-apt (either immaterial, invisible guardian angels exist or do not exist)/ However, the sentence is compatible with any state of affairs (any unfortunate state of affairs is easily explained by merely due to the inattentiveness of a guardian angel, for example).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Understood in this way, the problem of demarcation is somewhat similar to setting out what speech-acts can in principle give information about the world intersubjectively accessible to members of an epistemic community, and conversely &lt;i&gt;what we can in principle learn about the world&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: &amp;quot;times&amp;quot;; font-size: 12pt; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
We can think of the problem of demarcation in a more rigorous sense, as a question about whether it is possible to map the boundaries of what we can learn in principle through empirical inquiry. The sentence, &#39;All bachelors are unmarried men&#39; is not empirically informative, for it is analytic, but (so claimed Popper), neither is the synthetic existential statement, &#39;There exists a pearl which is ten times larger than the next largest pearl&#39; (Popper 1962b, S.2).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
As James Justus frames this understanding of the problem of the criterion, &#39;significance criteria simply attempt to indicate whether two domains are epistemically connected, for example, whether one statement class (e.g. observation statements) bears on the truth-values of another (e.g. hypotheses of theoretical science)? (Justus 2014, 417).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
With this framing of what function demarcation criteria generally serve, it now helps to examine Carnap overall motivations for adopting his demarcation criteria.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify; vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
4. Carnap&#39;s metaphilosophical approach&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Some preliminaries: oftentimes it does not do a service to give philosophers labels, as if labeling them will provide insight to their views. However, is appropriate to produce a few helpful labels for Carnap&#39;s approach as a loose conceptual scaffolding that rests upon itself, thereby reinforcing itself: we can say that Carnap adopted (in a sense, or something roughly like) a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;pragmatist theory of truth&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;, &lt;i&gt;conventionalism&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;linguistic pluralism&lt;/i&gt;. These three pillars help support &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;metaphysical deflationism&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;. These rough and ready labels will be elaborated on below in a way that helps fill in this conceptual scaffolding.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
5. Carnap&#39;s pragmatist theory of truth&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: &amp;quot;arial&amp;quot;; font-size: 16pt; font-weight: 400; vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Carnap notes the similarities between, in his eyes, the empiricist project and American pragmatism (1936, 26), and does not disagree when he says, ?Morris considers the two movements as complementary in their views, and as convergent in the directions of their present development.?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
With Carnap&#39;s interest in the similarities between the American pragmatist and logical empiricist movements in mind, Pierce&#39;s pragmatic maxim is important to cover briefly, since it helps clarify Carnap&#39;s metaphilosophical stance: ?Consider what effects, that might conceivably have practical bearings, we conceive the object of our conception to have. Then, our conception of these effects is the whole of our conception of the object? (1878). This is appropriate, since Carnap was faced with the problems that plagued much of Enlightenment philosophy, specifically the realisation that confidence in a theory, be the theory empirical or philosophical, did not track truth (understood under a more traditional Aristotle-inspired correspondence theory of truth).&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
The origins of this theory of truth within logical empiricist circles is in question, however. Quine traced this theory of truth--?the meaning of a statement is the method of empirically confirming or infirming it?--back to Peirce (1961, 37); other philosophers trace this back to Wittgenstein&#39;s &lt;i&gt;Tractatus&lt;/i&gt; (cf. 4.114, 4.11, 4.111 by way of Waismann 1930-1931).&amp;nbsp;This criterion of meaning is extended to encompass a criterion of truth, for determining the meaning of a sentence will determine the conditions of its truth.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Whichever origin, pragmatist or Wittgensteinian, this is undoubtedly one intellectual pillar Carnap built on in constructing his aversion to metaphysical speculation. Consequently, Carnap attempted to provide a different route for theory-preference that did not rely on what was, at the time, thought to be deficiencies in correspondence theories of truth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
The problem Carnap saw with correspondence theories of truth can be more or less put as follows: any preference for an attitude, theory or approach would be far better approached by what&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;practical implications&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;the concepts contained within that theory brings to the table. Truth-as-correspondence, however, simply did not carry with it any conceptual or practical weight in providing rational grounds for theory-preference, for it lacked any &lt;i&gt;criteria&lt;/i&gt; for truth. This placed the theory of correspondence in a dubious category, especially for empiricists already adverse to speculation on hidden features of the world accessible through inner speculation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
A &lt;i&gt;pragmatist&lt;/i&gt; theory of truth, on the other hand, provided clear and distinct criteria for truth, and was applicable to itself: the pragmatist theory of truth was itself pragmatically useful in the construction of our concepts.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
On this point, already it is clear that one traditional objection to Carnap may be made on spurious grounds: for example, if the analytic/synthetic distinction could not be maintained on &lt;i&gt;metaphysical&lt;/i&gt;, extra-linguistic&amp;nbsp;grounds, (as Quine claimed), &lt;i&gt;then so much for metaphysical grounds &lt;/i&gt;(Carnap could reply): these linguistic categories need only be grounded in their &lt;i&gt;pragmatic usefulness&lt;/i&gt;. There need not be anything over and above the demonstrated usefulness of a distinction in order to rationally adopt said distinction. If Quine is concerned over the fact that natural languages invite ambiguity, a Carnapian can easily respond that the existence of ambiguity does not demonstrate how these linguistic categories are no longer useful--they may simply be better than the alternative (that is, giving up on these linguistic categories).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In fact, if there exists ambiguity in natural languages, &lt;i&gt;what of it&lt;/i&gt;? Our sights are not set merely on what we have, but what we can &lt;i&gt;choose to do&lt;/i&gt;, that is, construct languages with a semantics and syntax that are &lt;i&gt;less&lt;/i&gt; ambiguous than natural languages. This further addresses the important distinction that Carnap draws between the use of natural languages and&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;artificially-constructed languages&lt;/i&gt;, which will be addressed in the next section on Carnap&#39;s conventionalism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify; vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
6. Carnap&#39;s conventionalism&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: &amp;quot;arial&amp;quot;; font-size: 16pt; font-weight: 400; vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Carnap&#39;s conventionalism can be viewed as an approach to philosophical methodology that rested on (in part) Carnap&#39;s rejection of a correspondence theory of truth. Without any correspondence between our concepts and features of the world independent of these concepts (or without any way to independently confirm whether there is a correspondence), there are no extra-linguistic criteria dictating the formulation of concepts. However, that does not entail that no criteria exist--we can choose whichever criteria best serve some ends, such as aiming at&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;conceptual clarity&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
When attempting to pin down a concept, we first figure out what we want the concept is to be used for, and then develop a concept that serves this function. Carnap refers to this as ?&lt;i&gt;explication&lt;/i&gt;? (Carnap 1951, S.2-5). Carnap (1962, S.2) describes this process as follows: ?The task of explication consists in transforming a given more or less inexact concept into an exact one or, rather, in replacing the first by the second. We call the given concept (or the term used for it) the &lt;i&gt;explicandum&lt;/i&gt;, and the exact concept proposed to take the place of the first (or the term proposed for it) the &lt;i&gt;explicatum&lt;/i&gt;. The &lt;i&gt;explicandum&lt;/i&gt; may belong to everyday language or to a previous stage in the development of scientific language.?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
There are no prior restrictions forbidding some course of action. In fact, Carnap (1934, S.17) states in ?Principle of Tolerance? that the logic of a language is entirely conventional, as well as our choice of logic (1928, S.107). Thus any approach to the categorisation of our language will not be justified by reference to ordinary language usage or intuitive judgments, but rather the construction of an artificial language system that helps clarify (or set boundaries on) the application of our own concepts (Carnap 1963, 938). The role of the philosopher is therefore (primarily) the &lt;i&gt;exploration of explications&lt;/i&gt;, aimed towards refinement and conceptual rigour.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Any formation of a concept will refer to ordinary language use and language intuitions and conventions, as well as pragmatic concerns. What is not made, however, is a justificatory bridge between ordinary language use and the formation of a concept such that ordinary language use provides a &lt;i&gt;justification&lt;/i&gt; for adopting an explication. Assuming such a justificatory bridge would be a mistake similar to attempts to justify ethical norms in terms of cultural or social norms.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Accordingly, an inference to the best explanation does not play any role in Carnap&#39;s choice to adopt or reject certain explicatums; rather, they are free choices based on whether they presently satisfy the task of explication: the applicability and fecundity of an explicatum proves its worth up until it no longer does, that is, until a rival explicatum is available that proves it worth even &lt;i&gt;better&lt;/i&gt; or it were to be discovered that the explicatum fails at its task, and a new explicatum must be developed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
This approach to philosophical methodology must be contrasted with methodologies of philosophy based on intuition, ordinary language, experimental philosophy or naturalised philosophy. Carnap&#39;s artificial language philosophy relies on the choice between language systems to solve philosophical problems (or puzzles or quiddles). The choice of language determines which sentences are to be treated as analytic and synthetic &lt;i&gt;in that language&lt;/i&gt;, while the choice of logic determines the strength of logical implication.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Carnap&#39;s motivation for artificial languages is explicitly a mimicry of approaches in the natural sciences. Indeed, ?[p]hilosophers, scientists, and mathematicians make explications very frequently? (Carnap 1962, S.3). Examples in the sciences are legion (e.g. Chang 2004). As Chang notes (mirroring Carnap) in his gloss of operationalism, ?The first thing we need to do is lose the habit of thinking of in terms of simple correctness. ? we need to keep in mind that those values are products of the operationalization in question, not independent standards against which we can judge the correctness of the operationalization itself? (206-208). Similarly, Stotz (2009, S.3) states, ?Empirical science is a powerhouse of conceptual innovation because scientists use and reuse their terminology in a truly ?exuberant? way. ? This only makes sense if we think of concepts as tools of research, as ways of classifying the experience shaped by experimentalists to meet their specific needs. Necessarily these tools get reshaped as the scientists? needs change.?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
This produces a division of labour between the philosopher and scientist: the role of philosophy is to solve a conceptual problem once empirical inquiry has been excluded as a fruitful endeavour. The philosopher is not irrelevant &lt;i&gt;per se&lt;/i&gt;, for they serve an important role in the empirical sciences; their purpose is not in competition with empirical science, either (Carnap 1934, &lt;i&gt;forward&lt;/i&gt;); it is not even an extension of the general empirical or critical methods of the natural sciences. Rather, the philosopher&#39;s job consists of a clarification and extension of the &lt;i&gt;conceptual methods&lt;/i&gt; of the natural sciences, prescribing a new language that is to be used by extending the general methods of &lt;i&gt;explication&lt;/i&gt; conducted by natural scientists into new domains.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
This Carnapian shift away from thinking ?in terms of simple correctness? and towards of ?concepts as tools of research, as ways of classifying the experience? underpins Carnap&#39;s own shift towards treating the role of the philosopher as engaged in an analysis of formal language rather than engaged in the attempt to solve philosophical problems (which will be addressed in the next section).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
As with the previous section, we can see that objecting the Carnap&#39;s conventionalist approach to demarcation on the grounds that any proposed demarcation criteria do not map on to the use of natural languages carries with it no threat to Carnap&#39;s criteria. Natural languages are likely to be inchoate and incoherent, hence the very desire that Carnap saw in aiming towards the construction of artificial languages in the natural sciences and his choice to emulate them in philosophy.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
It would be just as much an objection to claim that failures to intuitively group together the shapes and sizes of certain blocks (say, depending on the person, sometimes by colour, then by shape, but at other times by shape, then by colour) undermine a wholly different, &lt;i&gt;coherent&lt;/i&gt; scheme.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
To put this reply more precisely:&amp;nbsp;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: start;&#34;&gt;while criticisms from Putnam (1962) and others attempt to undermine this bipartition of language on the grounds that the vocabulary of science cannot be bipartitioned, Suppe (1971) notes Putnam&#39;s criticism relies on an analysis of our &lt;i&gt;ordinary&lt;/i&gt; language, while the introduction of a bipartition in a &lt;i&gt;formalised&lt;/i&gt; language is possible (Suppe 1972). In other words, Putnam criticises the artificial construction of languages as failing to adhere to the norms set out in ordinary language philosophy. But such a criticism is predicated on the assumption that a formalised language is impossible.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: start;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
While there may exist more exact criticisms of Carnap&#39;s overall approach, just by coming to understand Carnap&#39;s motivating reasons for adopting demarcation criteria, we can see that the more traditional narrative carries with it less argumentative force than before--to the point that the supposed culprit for the supposed death of logical empiricism could not be charged with the purported murder in a court of law: while there was motivation, the means and opportunity to kill &lt;i&gt;Carnap&#39;s programme&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;by way of dismantling the analytic/synthetic distinction were lacking.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
7. Carnap&#39;s linguistic pluralism&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
To understand Carnap&#39;s reasons for adopting linguistic analysis as the role of the philosopher requires addressing Carnap&#39;s concept of a &lt;i&gt;linguistic framework&lt;/i&gt;. Briefly, a linguistic framework sets the rules governing the use of predicates in some artificial language, for example, the terms used when speaking about observables or numbers. These speech-acts usually brings with it implicit ontological methods and questions, ?internal? to this form of discourse, which guides the division between these domains of discourse (Carnap 1947). If one were to ask, &#39;Are there numbers?&#39; the answer is trivial: if we are operating with a linguistic framework that uses numbers, the answer is trivial: yes. These just are the predicates and terms used in the linguistic framework. However, Carnap thought these ?internal? questions do not extend to questions about the &lt;i&gt;ontological status&lt;/i&gt; of predicates, such as ?Are there &lt;i&gt;really&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;numbers?? Carnap, instead, considers these questions ?external? to the linguistic framework. The question, &#39;Are there &lt;i&gt;really&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;numbers?&#39; is better understood as the question, &#39;Should we adopt the linguistic framework that uses numbers?&#39; The legitimate ?external? questions about the linguistic content of this framework extend only to whether we should &lt;i&gt;adopt a framework&lt;/i&gt;, as one would adopt a mode of speaking.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Carnap finds immense explanatory and instrumental use in this domain-carving: it explains why, for example, moral norms are not like laws of nature or the validity of an argument cannot be declared by fiat. The usefulness in setting out this distinction satisfies Pierce&#39;s maxim. Consequently, Carnap sets out to provide a robust demarcation criterion &lt;i&gt;between these apparent domains of discourse&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Carnap&#39;s aim in setting out a demarcation criterion is not value-neutral, however: he wants ?to explicate the boundary? between the empirical realm, which comprises both science and pseudo-science, and the realm of meaningless pseudo-statements? (1963, 878). &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Understood within the context of Carnap&#39;s early work, as Carnap put it, ?...the [Vienna] Circle rejected both the thesis of the reality of the external world and the thesis of its irreality as pseudo-statements; the same was the case for both the thesis of the reality of universals? and the nominalistic thesis that they are not real? (Carnap 1950, in 1956, 215).&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
These views are not unlike Carnap&#39;s own, although there is a subtle but important difference: if we approached the problem of articulating the extent of this apparent distinction between these domains, it must be approached first without assuming that the predicates and terms in each domain have referents, and that the sentences in each domain are truth-apt. With one blow Carnap does away with much of traditional metaphysics. The question, &#39;Are there &lt;i&gt;really&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;numbers?&#39; no longer has to do with questions about the ontological status of numbers, realism, nominalism, and so on.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Once we examine a linguistic framework that makes reference to objects that are subject to empirical inquiry, and are intersubjectively observable, it makes immense &lt;i&gt;practical&lt;/i&gt; sense to continue using a pre-theoretical understanding of ?true? and ?false? when speaking within this particular linguistic framework, for there remains a suitable criterion of truth, but this application of the terms ?true? and ?false? is not obviously so when our interest shifts to other linguistic frameworks. The criterion of pragmatic truth is &lt;i&gt;lacking&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
(&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;N.B.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;It should be noted that Carnap&#39;s approach is not a criterion explicating the meaning of a linguistic structure, only whether it is empirically significant, because the meaning of a sentence is accepted to be determined by both its empirical consequences and rules governing its use (Carnap 1939, section 25). This is in line with Popper&#39;s notion of a criterion demarcating between empirical and non-empirical sentences (Popper 1934/35, S.4, S.9; cf. Carnap 1963, S.6.A). Thus it only creates obfuscation to treat Carnap&#39;s criterion as that of &lt;i&gt;meaning&lt;/i&gt;, although Carnap repeatedly uses the term &#39;empirically meaningful&#39; in his writings. A more neutral way of framing this is to remove any discussion of criteria of meaning from an analysis of Carnap&#39;s motivations and criteria. However, since Carnap speaks frequently of issues relating to meaning and sense, whenever Carnap uses terms like ?meaningless? or ?pseudo-statement?, there should be pause. Further explanation for what Carnap means by ?meaningless? will be covered in the next section.)&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Teasing out the differences between Carnap&#39;s use of the phrase &#39;empirical meaning&#39; from more everyday use of the term &#39;meaning&#39; shows how the oft-repeated objection that demarcation criteria are self-refuting (seen in, for example, Popper 1935) targets a &lt;i&gt;position never held by Carnap&lt;/i&gt;, and is in fact fundamentally &lt;i&gt;at odds with&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Carnap&#39;s position&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
With these three pillars of pragmatism, conventionalism and linguistic pluralism, Carnap&#39;s criteria of confirmability and disconfirmability are instead a proposal or convention for how to proceed in our choice of differing linguistic systems, rather than a statement embedded within the linguistic systems we choose. It would be as fruitful to object to, for example, the biologist&#39;s criteria for sorting between different types of cells by noting the criteria are themselves not cells. The only appropriate response to this kind of objection would be pursed lips and a furrowed brow, since it reveals that a person has misunderstood some fundamental concept.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
8. Carnap&#39;s metaphysical deflationism&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
In a rough way of viewing Carnap, Carnap could be seen as a pluralist about ontological commitment, yet remains deflationary about &lt;i&gt;whether there exists any corresponding domains beyond their use&lt;/i&gt;; consequently, Carnap should be understood as more of a &lt;i&gt;linguistic pluralist&lt;/i&gt;. If Carnap were to be an ontological pluralist, then Carnap&#39;s views would collapse into a form of realism or anti-realism about the existence of entities outside a linguistic framework. Carnap, however, is simply &lt;i&gt;disinterested&lt;/i&gt; in that discussion, as one would be disinterested in answering the question of whether there did or did not exist intangible, invisible guardian angels. Without any way to determine whether or not they exist, questions such as &#39;Do intangible, invisible guardian angels exist?&#39; are rephrased as questions such as &#39;Should we adopt a framework in which there are predicates and terms such as &#34;guardian angels&#34;?&#39;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
It is helpful to frame Carnap&#39;s metaphysical speculation in light of the use-mention distinction. Carnap believed the legitimate use of terms like ?number? are &#39;internal&#39;, and its use are dictated by the rules of the linguistic framework. Questions over whether or not numbers exist would be to commit a use-mention fallacy, since external questions outside a linguistic framework mention the terms in question, rather than use them. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
In Carnap&#39;s eyes, we should treat much of traditional metaphysics as ?meaningless? &lt;i&gt;as a matter of convention&lt;/i&gt;, as ?meaningless? when attempting to express them in whatever formalised language is adopted. This preserves much of applied ethics, mathematics and logic, but eliminates talk &lt;i&gt;about&lt;/i&gt; these fields, specifically whether their content is truth-apt. The same is true, naturally, of talk about whether there is any inaccessible truth or falsity to some synthetic proposition external to that language. In sum, &lt;i&gt;motivations for accepting Carnap&#39;s demarcation problem rests on accepting the pragmatic usefulness of a theory of separate language domains&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
It should be emphasised here that Carnap has &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; thrown much of traditional philosophy on the pyre: Carnap&#39;s target is only the forms of philosophical discourse that inquire into whether there exist truth-makers for sentences and referents for these predicates and terms from a higher-order linguistic framework that applies to differing linguistic frameworks. Much of the realism/anti-realism debates in philosophy are simply asking the wrong sorts of questions.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Take, for example, Feigl&#39;s sentence, ?Everything is doubling in size every ten minutes?. We cannot learn through experience that the sentence is true or false. Therefore, according to Carnap, the sentence, like its negation, simply ought not to be of the concern of scientists or philosophers, since, while it may be synthetic, &lt;i&gt;it is not empirically significant&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
These sorts of sentences, as well as sentences about our predicates that surreptitiously ask whether a predicate corresponds to some fact of the world, are to be considered on par with much of traditional metaphysics, that is, simply not analysable in a way that permits robust and informative explication. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
By way of a tortured metaphor, Carnap believes we are caught within the linguistic prison, and thus our focus should be on mapping the walls of this prison; we can, however, shift these walls to accommodate our needs by introducing a rigorous floor plan; any shift to the inner structure, though, should be done only on principled grounds. In this way, Pierce&#39;s pragmatist criterion of truth holds on both the level of what criterion of demarcation should be accepted but also on the level of on what grounds a criterion of demarcation is to be accepted.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
8. A summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Carnap&#39;s&amp;nbsp;&lt;i style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;pragmatist theory of truth&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;, &lt;i&gt;conventionalism &lt;/i&gt;and&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;linguistic pluralism&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;are separate pieces of a broader programme that, when resting upon each other, mutually supports and motivates Carnap&#39;s&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;metaphysical deflationism.&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;By setting out what these positions are in the best available light, two commonplace arguments against Carnap&#39;s demarcation criteria--(1) the criteria are self-refuting; (2) the criteria are parasitic on the analytic/synthetic distinction, and the distinction does not unambiguously apply to natural languages--reveal more about the misunderstandings of Carnap&#39;s critics than they reveal any viable objections to Carnap&#39;s programme.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;I must repeat myself here: I am not a scholar on Carnap, and could be completely off the mark; however, after reading Carnap&#39;s work more and more, and reading some modern defences of Carnap that are in line with my own assessment and interpretation of Carnap, it is difficult to see how Carnap&#39;s critics could have both voiced these criticisms seriously and read Carnap charitably.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
Bibliography&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Ayer, A.J.&amp;nbsp;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;1946.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;Language, Truth and Logic&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;, 2nd edition London: Victor Gollancz Ltd.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;Carnap, R. 1928, &lt;i&gt;Der logische Aufbau der Welt&lt;/i&gt;, Berlin-Schalchtensee: Weltkreis Verlag&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;_______. 1934.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;The Logical Syntax of Language&lt;/i&gt;, trans. Amethe Smeaton, London: Routledge, and Kegan Paul.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;_______. 1936. Testability and Meaning,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;Philosophy of Science&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;, 3(4): 419-471.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
_______. 1947. Empiricism, Semantics and Ontology in &lt;i&gt;Meaning and Necessity&lt;/i&gt;, Chicago: University of Chicago Press.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
_______. 1950. Empiricism, Semantics, and Ontology, &lt;i&gt;Revue Internationale de Philosophie&lt;/i&gt; 4:20-40, reprinted in&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Meaning and Necessity&lt;/i&gt;, University of Chicago Press, 1956, 215.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;_______. 1951.&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;The Nature and Application of Inductive Logic&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
_______. 1962. &lt;i&gt;Logical Foundations of Probability&lt;/i&gt;, Chicago: University of Chicago Press.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
_______. 1963. Replies and Systematic Expositions, &lt;i&gt;The Philosophy of Rudolf Carnap&lt;/i&gt;, ed. Paul. A. Schilpp.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Chang, H. 2004.&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Inventing Temperature.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Church, A.&amp;nbsp;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;1949. Review: Alfred Jules Ayer,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;Language, Truth and Logic&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;, Journal of Symbolic Logic, 14(1): 52-53.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
Hempel, C.&amp;nbsp;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;1950. Problems and Changes in the Empiricist Criterion of Meaning,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;Revue Internationale de Philosophie&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;, 41(11): 41-63.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;______. 1951. The Concept of Cognitive Significance: A Reconsideration, &lt;i&gt;Proceedings of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences&lt;/i&gt;, 80(1):61-77.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;Justus, J. 2014. Carnap&#39;s Forgotten Criterion of Empirical Significance,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;Soames, S. 2003. The Rise and Fall of the Empiricist Criterion of Meaning, in&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;Philosophical Analysis in the Twentieth Century&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;, Princeton: Princeton University Press.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: start;&#34;&gt;Suppe, F. 1971. On Partial Interpretation, &lt;i&gt;The Journal of Philosophy&lt;/i&gt;, 68(3): 57-76.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: start;&#34;&gt;_______. 1972. What&#39;s Wrong with the Received View on the Structure of Scientific Theories?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;text-align: start;&#34;&gt;Philosophy of Science&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: start;&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: start;&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;39(1):1-19.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;Stotz, K. 2009. Experimental Philosophy of Biology: Notes from the field, &lt;i&gt;Studies in History and Philosophy of Science Part A&lt;/i&gt;, 40:233-237&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;Pierce, C.S.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;1878.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;How to Make Our Ideas Clear&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;, Popular Science Monthly, 12: 286-302.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;Popper, K.R&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;. 1934/35. &lt;i&gt;Logik der Forschung: zur Erkenntnistheorie der Modernen Naturwissenschaft&lt;/i&gt;. Vienna: Springer-Verlag.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;_______.1962a. The Demarcation between Science and Metaphysics, in &lt;i&gt;Conjectures and Refutations&lt;/i&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;New York: Basic Books.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;_______. 1962b. On the Status of Science and of Metaphysics, in&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Conjectures and Refutations&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;Putnam, H. 1962.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;What Theories are Not in &amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Logic, Methodology and Philosophy of Science&lt;/i&gt;, ed. Ernest Nagel, Patrick Suppes, and Alfred Tarski, Stanford, Cal.: Stanford University Press: 240-252.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;Quine, W.V.O. 1961, Two Dogmas of Empiricism,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;From a Logical Point of View&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;, Harvard: Harvard University Press.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;Waismann, F. 1930-1931. Logische Analyse des Wahrscheinlichkeitsbegriff,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;Erkenntnis&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;, 1 228-248.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;15/8/2017&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color: transparent; vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;span id=&#34;docs-internal-guid-6f36616a-a897-0df4-7052-f21dad760f6c&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A far better objection to normative demarcation criteria</title>
      <link>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/post/better/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/post/better/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
These are follow-up notes on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://nathanoseroff.blogspot.co.uk/2017/08/one-obviously-poor-and-one-disputable.html&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; on how to present plausible objections to normative demarcation criteria. In it, I present a brief overview of a problem related to the &lt;i&gt;value problem&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;in epistemology, then illustrate two ways of framing any &#39;final value&#39; to normative demarcation criteria by examining &#39;early&#39; and &#39;later&#39; Karl Popper&#39;s views on the subject. I end by presenting the mature objection raised by Paul Feyerabend that targets both views held by &#39;early&#39; and &#39;later&#39; Popper.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
1. Which values are appropriate?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Here is a far better objection than the REA and CEA, and the objection raised by Lakatos, Feyerabend and Kuhn. It begins with the following question: why accept Popper&#39;s normative demarcation criteria set out in (1)-(7)? For that matter, why accept &lt;i&gt;any&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;methodological principle? There are a number of potential answers. For example, it may be because they are...&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
(a) valuable in-themselves. There is no other rationale: scientists ought to put forward theoretical systems of ever-increasing coherent empirical content and unifying explanatory breadth and depth because scientists and philosophers of science agree that is a desirable aim.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
(b) there are non-truth-related grounds for why we should adopt them. It may be &lt;i&gt;socially&lt;/i&gt; or &lt;i&gt;ethically&lt;/i&gt; desirable to produce explanations that unify disparate fields or set out the limits of what is possible.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
(c) there is some &lt;i&gt;epistemically&lt;/i&gt; valuable reason that isn&#39;t aimed at &lt;i&gt;truth&lt;/i&gt;, nor seen as a derivative aim of the pursuit of truth, but is nevertheless desirable. That is, ever-increasing empirical content, simplicity and universality of explanations may be epistemically valuable even if these explanations do not aim at truth.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
(d) there is some truth-related epistemically valuable reason: these rules aim at empirical adequacy, truth,  truthlikeness, aim away from falsehood, etc.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
This is a problem of determining whether the grounds for demarcation rules are suitable. (a) terminates without any further grounds, while (b) makes the problem of demarcation no longer relevant to epistemology or philosophy of science.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
While it certainly would be a greater benefit were (b) to be true &lt;i&gt;in addition &lt;/i&gt;to other grounds, neither (a) nor (b) seem particularly desirable &lt;i&gt;on their own&lt;/i&gt;. If (b) were accepted and it was a matter of mere &lt;i&gt;convention&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;that we accept these rules, we would desire something over and above mere convention--convention &lt;i&gt;alone &lt;/i&gt;does not entail obligation to uphold convention. Therefore, our sights turn to (c) and (d) as plausible candidates.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Only if (c) and (d) are exhausted and found wanting as plausible grounds should we determine whether (a) and (b) are true, and hopefully the available grounds remain normative, such as finally terminating in an ethical or argumentative imperative to behave in certain ways and refrain from behaving in other ways.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
(c) may fare no better: it seems little more than a restatement of (a), with the added benefit that these grounds are somehow valuable for an additional reason--they are not merely valuable in-themselves, but valuable because they are valuable in-themselves &lt;i&gt;and&lt;/i&gt; this value is considered a core epistemic principle (although unrelated to truth).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
This issue shows that grounding demarcation criteria produces an issue related to--but fully distinct from--the&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;value problem&lt;/i&gt;. The earlier &lt;i&gt;Meno problem&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;helps sketch out the value problem. It&amp;nbsp;is as follows: if knowledge is distinctively more valuable than mere true belief, what is that value over and above simply believing truly? As an illustration, it could be that, as Socrates claimed, knowledge is &#39;tied-down&#39; to the truth, in a way that prevents the easy loss of true beliefs, but any number of dogmatically-held true beliefs that fall short of knowledge may be &#39;tied-down&#39; to the truth just as strongly.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
While the value problem is related to explicating the final value of &lt;i&gt;knowledge&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;that is over and above the value of mere true belief, demarcationists are left with the problem of explicating the final value of certain &lt;i&gt;methodological norms&lt;/i&gt;. Is it (a), (b), (c) or (d) (or some combination of the above)? &lt;i&gt;Is&lt;/i&gt; there some final value (or should we act &lt;i&gt;as if&lt;/i&gt; there is some final value?), or should demarcationists be value-pluralists, accepting more than one final value of demarcation criteria?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
We therefore have the following question for philosophers of science: &lt;i&gt;why should we believe unifying theories with immense explanatory depth and breadth are valuable&lt;/i&gt;?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
There is, furthermore, a second question for the demarcationist: assume we have answered the first problem and have accepted some final value(s) for proposed demarcation rules. Since the REA and CEA are not permissible objections to demarcation rules and the historical objection raised by Lakatos &lt;i&gt;et al&lt;/i&gt;. cannot lead to revising normative demarcation rules, there is no obvious empirical evidence available to check whether implementing a proposed rule will reliably lead to successfully attaining the desired final value(s). Why should we believe, for example, that testing theories will, in the long run, direct us towards the truth or away from error? We could operate on the &lt;i&gt;assumption&lt;/i&gt; that adhering to the rule is more reliable than &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;testing our theories--however, that doesn&#39;t resolve this problem. We could very well operate on a different assumption that adhering to a different rule is preferable because it is more reliable than other approaches. Which rule is to be preferred, then, and on what grounds?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4 style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
2. What are these norms or rules &lt;i&gt;aimed&lt;/i&gt; at?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
It helps to examine this problem by focusing again on Popper&#39;s collection of methodological rules: they purportedly help the scientific community direct themselves towards certain short-term ends, namely (1) eliminating error, and (2) increasing the empirical content of theoretical systems. These are two short-term strategies that are, in turn, aimed at long-term goals.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The first question is raised:&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;why&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;are these ends valuable? Are they valuable in-themselves? Valuable for non-epistemic ends? Valuable for epistemic (but not truth-related) ends? Or valuable for truth-related ends?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
There is some tension in Popper&#39;s thought over the final aims of scientific practice: in &lt;i&gt;The Logic of Scientific Discovery&lt;/i&gt;, Popper claims &#39;it is possible to avoid using the concepts &#34;true&#34; and &#34;false&#34;&#39; in the construction of aims (2002, 273, cf. 275)--progress is viewed as a matter of finding theories with increasing explanatory and predictive power. This would eliminate (d) as the final value, leaving (a), (b) and (c) as candidate ends.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
If one aligned themselves with &#39;early Popper&#39;, certain normative rules like aiming towards increasing the predictive and explanatory content of theories would be aimed at satisfying a &#39;supreme rule&#39; (2002, 33) of making a certain set of speech-acts as empirically informative as possible. Furthermore, other rules insure this set of speech-acts are not protected against future testing in any way by refusing to adopt certain argumentative stratagems, such as making &lt;i&gt;ad hoc&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;adjustments to the theoretical system, all aimed at satisfying this &#39;supreme rule&#39;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The first question is raised once more: &lt;i&gt;why&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;is this &#39;supreme rule&#39; valuable? Is it valuable in-itself? Valuable for non-epistemic ends? Valuable for epistemic (but not truth-related) ends?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
The reasons to adopt the &#39;supreme rule&#39; is nothing but &#39;a proposal for an agreement or convention&#39; by individuals with certain argumentative or ethical standards, such as a desire to avoid dogmatism, a desire to speak informatively and address &#39;new and unexpected questions, challenging us to try out new and hitherto undreamed-of answers&#39; (ibid. 15). This is an &#39;infinite yet attainable aim: that of ever discovering new, and more general problems, and of subjecting our ever tentative answers to ever renewed and ever more rigorous tests&#39; (ibid. 281).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Note that there is no reference made to ultimate &lt;i&gt;epistemic&lt;/i&gt; standards such as truth, but rather socially agreed-upon conventions that withstand criticism--including, but not exclusive to, the socially agreed-upon convention that a particular methodology is truth-conducive or truth-directed. In short, &#39;early Popper&#39; grounds this &#39;supreme rule&#39; in extra-epistemic grounds, namely (a) and (b). These simply are the &#39;rules of the game&#39; of science. Popper presents these rules as candidates and offers them up for criticism. Other philosophers of science may improve on these rules, or show how these rules may be abandoned. By this process of conjecture and criticism, we can arrive at a (provisionally) stable position.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
3. Why accept these &#39;rules of the game&#39; for scientists?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
On what grounds can any proposed &#39;rules of the game&#39; for scientists be preferred? Popper&#39;s approach swallows all disciplines: if the &#39;rules of the game&#39; for &lt;i&gt;scientists&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;are socially agreed-upon conventions that withstand criticism, what is good for the goose is good for the gander:&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;philosophers of science&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;subject &lt;i&gt;aims&lt;/i&gt; to criticism in the hopes of improving or rejecting these aims, as well as proposing interesting and novel rules (and aims) that supplement or replace these rules and aims.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In short, Popper&#39;s approach is &lt;i&gt;ecumenical&lt;/i&gt;: nothing at the onset &lt;i&gt;forbids&lt;/i&gt; the introduction of a final value (such as approximating the truth), but furthermore nothing &lt;i&gt;demands&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;introducing a final value. It is simply up for philosophers of science (and scientists) to engage in critical disputation over which final value(s) should be preferred over others. Perhaps there are many, or merely one; perhaps it is agreed that it all bottoms out in convention, in ethical imperatives to treat others as rational agents deserving of a hearing, or there is the conventional agreement to take the final value as truth. It is up to philosophers to discuss amongst one another and--eventually--decide over what aims are desirable.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
We have a second-order problem, namely, philosophers are faced with two intertwined paths: philosophers can (1) conventionally agree to accept or reject certain rules, and (2) conventionally agree to accept or reject certain aims. The moment, however, we take either rules or aims to be beyond question, we stop playing the &#39;game of philosophy&#39;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
But why accept these &#39;rules of the game&#39; for philosophers? Here is one answer: presumably, these &#39;rules of the game&#39; are accepted for the same reason why the &#39;rules of the game&#39; for scientists are adopted--these &#39;rules of the game&#39; avoid dogmatism, increase the informativeness of our speech-acts and open up henceforth unarticulated and interesting questions. If there is something objectionable to any of these starting aims, they will be eventually uncovered, so long as philosophers of science and diligent, quick-witted and fortunate to discover some objection to these rules and aims.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Similarly, if there is something (henceforth unarticulated) valuable to be found in dogmatism, threats or violence, then they may be eventually uncovered, since these pathways are not closed from our starting point, either. However, these ways do not look promising, since they do not discriminate in their &lt;i&gt;content&lt;/i&gt;: &lt;i&gt;any&lt;/i&gt; position can be defended come what may by being dogmatic, threats or violence, and would (presumably) end the &#39;game of philosophy&#39; prematurely by adopting them.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
4. &#39;Later Popper&#39;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
By the time of the publication of&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Conjectures and Refutations&lt;/i&gt; (1963) &#39;later Popper&#39; defends a different aim for scientific progress: an increase in explanatory and predictive power is valuable &lt;i&gt;because it is aimed at truth&lt;/i&gt; (ibid. 226), for &#39;we simply cannot do without something like this idea of a better or worse approximation to truth&#39; (ibid. 232). While &#39;early Popper&#39; is a value-pluralist, and believed truth-as-correspondence may be one of many potential aims (but is not necessary from the onset), now &#39;later Popper&#39; is a value-monist: the one final aim is, so Popper thought, &lt;i&gt;approximation to truth&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
It is clear that both approaches are compatible with Popper&#39;s later work on critical rationalism: without any strong fulcrum with which to lift up the rest of the intellectual scaffolding, there is no Wittgensteinian &#39;hinge proposition&#39; or &#39;Archimedean point&#39;; we are left with a radical form of fallibilism, the &#39;early&#39; version on which begins with no reference to truth or falsity (although such an avenue is open to exploration) and the later version has gone down this route and concluded that the best available way to explain why one theoretical system is preferable to another is by recourse to their relative degrees of &lt;i&gt;verisimilitude&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
It is easy to see how adopting these methodological rules will reliably secure the ends of &#39;early Popper&#39;; however, it is not as clear how &#39;late Popper&#39; can. In fact, it seems an article of faith that any proposed methodological rule in the sciences will reliably aim towards the truth, without assuming some questionable metaphysical assumptions on the relationship between any features of a theoretical system--such as explanatory or predictive power--and truth. Value-monism is on shakier argumentative grounds than value-pluralism. That is, it remains an open question over whether the world is so constructed that broad and deep explanations are more likely to capture any underlying, hidden features of the world than narrow and shallow explanations.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
If we are to be value-pluralists, and avoid dogmatism, desire to speak informatively and and always address new and interesting problems, &lt;i&gt;without any final goal of truth&lt;/i&gt;, it is &lt;i&gt;here&lt;/i&gt; that Feyerabend raises his strongest objection against normative demarcation criteria by (perhaps inadvertently) producing a &lt;i&gt;reductio&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;for the &#39;early Popper&#39;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
5. Feyerabend&#39;s objection&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Feyerabend introduced his aim of &lt;i&gt;theoretical pluralism&lt;/i&gt; as &#39;an essential part of the empirical method&#39; (1999a, 91): Feyerabend extends Popper&#39;s early work on critical experiments, noting that absent the existence of alternative theories, severe testing is likely to be impossible after some time, without good fortune. Without a rival theory, we are left in a holding pattern, without an idea of where to look for a severe test of a theoretical system. Feyereabend begins his argument for theoretical pluralism by attacking &#39;the assumption of the relative autonomy of facts, or the autonomy principle&#39; (ibid, 91):&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In Feyerabend&#39;s words, &#39;Not only is the description of every single fact dependent on some theory (which may, of course, be very different from the theory to be tested). There exist also facts which cannot be unearthed except with the help of alternatives to the theory to be tested, and which become unavailable as soon as such alternatives are excluded&#39; (ibid. 91-21).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Thus &#39;[t]he methodological unit to which we must refer when discussing questions of test and empirical content is constituted by a whole set of partly overlapping, factually adequate, but mutually  inconsistent theories&#39; (ibid. 92).&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Consequently, we have a &lt;i&gt;principle of proliferation&lt;/i&gt;, which aims at satisfying the ends set out by &#39;early Popper&#39;: &#39;&lt;i&gt;Invent and elaborate theories which are inconsistent with the accepted point of view, even if the latter should happen to be highly confirmed and generally accepted&lt;/i&gt;&#39; (1981, 105). In this way, scientists are rarely--if ever--caught in a holding pattern.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
That is not to say that Feyerabend&#39;s theoretical pluralism on its own&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;is at odds&lt;/i&gt; with Popper&#39;s later approach. In fact, Feyerabend credits Popper with being the first to point out &#39;the need, in the process of the refutation of a theory, for at least another theory&#39; (1962, 32). Rather, it shows that Feyerabend extends &lt;i&gt;both&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;&#39;early Popper&#39; and Popper&#39;s later approach by introducing his principle of proliferation: there are no prior restrictions laid down on what rival theories we can introduce, and we should do our best to produce as many as possible in order to develop surprising and novel ways to test them.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Other proposals by Feyerabend focus on the short-term, tactical level, such as, for example, his proposal called the &#39;&lt;i&gt;principle of tenacity&lt;/i&gt;&#39;, dictating that scientists ought to stick to promising theories &#39;despite considerable difficulties&#39; (1999b, 107). &amp;nbsp;This proposal seems to be an improvement to both &#39;early Popper&#39; and &#39;later Popper&#39;, since it makes explicit Popper&#39;s observation that any crucial experiment is never uncontroversial: what appears to be a &lt;i&gt;reductio&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;may in fact be a surprising consequence of a theory. Think of, for example, how the Popper experiment and EPR experiment did not refute certain interpretations of quantum mechanics, but rather was a crucial experiment that &lt;i&gt;corroborated&lt;/i&gt; these interpretations.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
However, Feyerabend also included some eliminative proposals, such as in the first edition of &lt;i&gt;Against Method&lt;/i&gt;, Feyerabend suggested removing the condition of &#39;factual adequacy&#39; (1975, 41, fn. 8), thus repudiating later Popper&#39;s final aim of approximation to truth. Since traditional epistemic standards of aiming at truth are no longer paramount, all theories are &#39;scientific&#39; in both a descriptive and normative sense, &lt;i&gt;so long as they are empirically significant and add to the proliferation of theories&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Feyerabend&#39;s rejection of &#39;factual adequacy&#39; can also be seen as an over-extension of Popper&#39;s critical rationalism to embrace &#39;a radically sceptical interpretation of Popper&#39;s own philosophy of science&#39; (Lakatos 1978, 166, fn. 2): high-level theoretical systems are not just tested by appealing to other, accepted, low-level theoretical systems describing some space-time region &lt;i&gt;K&lt;/i&gt;; they are now tested by appealing to &lt;i&gt;other&lt;/i&gt; high-level theoretical systems. No longer are &#39;basic statements&#39; limited to what is intersubjectively agreed-upon by recourse to experimentation and testing, but simply what is agreed-upon, irrespective to whether there is an appeal to an empirical basis of testing.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
This proposal itself was criticised by Hilary Putnam as the claim that scientists ought to strive for &#39;alternative explanations by means of false theories&#39;, so that progress is not approximation to truth, but rather the explosion of a sea of theories which &#39;will later turn out to be false, and will be superseded by new batteries of false theories&#39; (1975, 119).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
It is here that Feyerabend&#39;s far more mature objection to Popper becomes clear: without the ability to appeal to any empirical evidence of the superiority of scientists maintaining truth as a regulative ideal or goal (for the REA, CEA and tactical objections are impermissible), on what grounds should we prefer Popper&#39;s goal of &lt;i&gt;approximating truth&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;over Feyerabend&#39;s far more practical goal of&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;proliferation&lt;/i&gt;?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
We may &lt;i&gt;desire&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;approximation of truth, but others may also desire nothing beyond proliferation. We are left with this choice, and there are no obvious arguments for one over the other; rather, it is a matter of aesthetic preference, rather than providing a rationale for preferring truth over proliferation. We are therefore caught in a bind: we can desire truth, but have no compelling arguments to believe any rules will help guide us towards truth; or we can desire proliferation, and aim at something easily obtainable.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
Bibliography&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Feyerabend, P.K. (1962). Explanation, reduction and empiricism. In H. Feigl, &amp;amp; G. Maxwell (Eds) &lt;i&gt;Scientific explanation, space and time&lt;/i&gt;. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press: 28-97.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
_______. (1975). &lt;i&gt;Against Method&lt;/i&gt;. London: Verso.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
_______. (1981.) Reply to criticism. Comments on Smart, Sellars and Putnam. In P.K. Feyerabend, &lt;i&gt;Realism, rationalism and scientific method. Philosophical papers, Vol. 1.&lt;/i&gt; Cambridge: Cambridge University Press: 104--131.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
_______. (1987). &lt;i&gt;Farewell to Reason&lt;/i&gt;. London: Verso.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
_______. (1999a). How to be a good empiricist. A plea for tolerance in matters epistemological. In P.K. Feyerabend, &lt;i&gt;Knowledge, Science and Relativism. Philosophical Papers, Vol. 3&lt;/i&gt;. Ed. J. Preston. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press: 78--103.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
_______. (1999b). Outline of a pluralistic theory of knowledge and action. In P.K. Feyabend, &lt;i&gt;Knowledge, Science and Relativism&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Lakatos, I. (1978). Popper on demarcation and induction. In I. Lakatos, &lt;i&gt;Philosophical Papers, Vol 1: The methodology of scientific research programmes.&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;Ed J. Worrall and G. Currie. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press: 139-167.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Popper, K. (1935) [2002]. &lt;i&gt;The Logic of Scientific Discovery&lt;/i&gt;. London: Routledge.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
______. (1963). &lt;i&gt;Conjectures and Refutations&lt;/i&gt;. London: Routledge &amp;amp; Kegan Paul.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Putnam, H. (1975). How not to talk about meaning. In H. Putnam, &lt;i&gt;Philosophical papers, Vol. 2: Mind, Language and Reality&lt;/i&gt;, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. 117--131.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
12/8/17&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One obviously poor and one disputable good objection to normative demarcation criteria</title>
      <link>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/post/disputable/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/post/disputable/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
I present one patently poor--but popular--objection to &#39;normative&#39; demarcation criteria. This objection can be put as follows: there is a disjunct between the normative rule and historical adherence to the rule. It is often (mistakenly) attributed to Imre Lakatos, Paul Feyerabend and Thomas Kuhn. I then show why this objection is misdirected against all proposed solutions to normative problems of demarcation.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
I then present the more nuanced objection seen in Lakatos, Feyerabend and (implicitly) Kuhn&#39;s writings. This objection was thought to be the death knell of normative demarcation criteria distinct from history of science. The objection runs as follows: there is a disjunct between what we ought to do in the long-term based on these normative criteria and what we ought to do in the short-term based on a desire to avoid falsehoods and preserve truths. The traditional normative demarcation project seen in, for example, Karl Popper, is therefore &#39;superseded&#39; by the &#39;historical&#39; turn in Lakatos, &lt;i&gt;et al&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
I explain how clarifying the more subtle objection is enough to show that it is overstated. Thus, Popper&#39;s solution doesn&#39;t succumb to this form of objection, although there are ways to improve Popper&#39;s approach--specifically by incorporating insights by Feyerabend, Lakatos and Kuhn. Furthermore, no other proposed ahistorical solution to the normative problem similarly succumbs to similar objections. The traditional ahistorical project isn&#39;t superseded by the historical turn per se; rather, the two play different functions in philosophy of science with different areas of focus.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4 style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
1. The empirical argument against normative demarcation criteria&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
There is one objection that is often directed at normative demarcation criteria. It runs more or less as follows:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
The &lt;i&gt;refuting empirical argument&lt;/i&gt; (REA): Certain methodological or normative rules or &#39;best practices&#39; in the sciences are not, or have not been, followed in scientific practice. These rules stand refuted by the empirical evidence, and therefore should be rejected on those grounds.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
An example of this argument can be found in Deutscher (1968). This objection is, as far as I have seen, almost exclusively directed at Popper&#39;s normative demarcation criteria, however it applies just as (in)effectively to other proposed normative criteria.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
I expect that if more attention is directed at more modern-day normative demarcation criteria proposed in, for example, Pigliucci and Boudry&#39;s edited volume, &lt;i&gt;Philosophy of Pseudoscience&lt;/i&gt; (2013), we should see a resurgence in this same (very poor) objection in the coming decades.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Upon more than a moment&#39;s reflection, it is clear that REA is not a cogent criticism. Here are two reasons why.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
First: some (perhaps many) scientists will on occasion follow bad practices. It would make as much sense to argue that since certain normative rules or &#39;best practices&#39; in policing are not, or have not been, followed by police officers, these rules stand similarly refuted by the empirical evidence. Unlike laws of nature, we can and have violated normative or behaviour-binding epistemic and moral rules. The proper response to this conflict between rule and behaviour is to conclude people have failed to adhere to these rules, not treat these rules as being refuted by the empirical evidence.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Second: it is possible, that despite the apparent successes in the natural sciences, that most scientists have failed to uphold these normative rules. Even then, this would not constitute a refutation of these norms. Although it would be &lt;i&gt;prima facie&lt;/i&gt; strange that a norm did not &#39;square&#39; with even paradigmatic examples of &#39;best practices&#39;, at most it may lead us to suspect the proposed normative demarcation criteria require an additional explanation for continued apparent success in spite of--rather than because of--adherence to the rule.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
A corollary of the REA is another argument. Call it CEA:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
The &lt;i&gt;confirming empirical argument&lt;/i&gt; (CEA): Certain methodological or normative rules or &#39;best practices&#39; in the sciences are, or have been, followed in scientific practice. These rules stand supported by the empirical evidence, and therefore should be accepted on those grounds.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
The first and second reason for rejecting REA are mirrored in the rejection of SEA: even if all scientists behaved in ways that adhered to a normative criterion of demarcation, it would not follow that the norm received empirical support. This result may be, however, a bit more surprising, but only if we fail to realise we have smuggled in the assumption that most scientists behave in ways that we believe are worth emulating. What we believe is worth emulating may be mistaken.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
REA and CEA both implicitly include the following two assumptions:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
A: Good scientific practice is such-and-such.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
B: Most scientists adhere to good scientific practice.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Without assuming A&amp;amp;B, the entirety of REA and CEA are argumentatively empty. The original objection is revealed to be the following implicit argument:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
1. Good scientific practice is such-and-such.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
2. Most scientists adhere to good scientific practice.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
3. If scientists follow a proposed normative demarcation, scientists will no longer adhere to good practice.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
4. Therefore, a proposed normative demarcation criterion at odds with such-and-such conflicts with good scientific practice.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
So much for the REA and CEA.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
There is a further puzzling result: if we reject the REA and CEA, no empirical evidence could (at least on its own) support or refute a normative demarcation criterion. But what use is there for history of science if history of science cannot inform attempts at solving the normative demarcation problem? If REA and CEA are rejected, attempts at describing &#39;normal&#39; scientific practice tell philosophers of science nothing. The entire &#39;historical&#39; turn seen in Lakatos, Feyerabend and Kuhn would be (presumably) predicated on a mistake.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4 style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
2. Properly appraising proposed normative demarcation criteria&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
A good working assumption is that this conclusion is (obviously) mistaken. Some of the best philosophers of science in the 1970s cannot have overlooked these problems with the REA and CEA.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Here&#39;s one way to skirt this problem and salvage the plausibility of the &#39;historical&#39; turn: methodological or normative demarcation criteria don&#39;t assert that scientists in fact follow rules of appraising theories or their behaviour. Rather, they specify (a) an aim or group of aims, and (b) a set of rules for satisfying those aims.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
It is the job of a philosopher arguing in favour of normative demarcation criteria to specify (c) why this aim is both worthwhile and realisable, as well as (d) provide (plausible) reasons for why these rules will (plausibly) satisfy those aims faster, easier and/or more reliably than (known) alternative rules.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
If we are to criticise any proposed normative demarcation criteria, we must criticise (a) and (b) on &lt;i&gt;these&lt;/i&gt; grounds--their failure to satisfy either (c) or (d), rather than the REA and CEA.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
A proposed normative demarcation criterion that is not realisable would be like an ethical norm that could not be put into practice--it may be worthwhile, but we cannot realise it. That is not to say that we should not still aim at it; rather, some nearby aims may be preferable because they are more realisable, given our epistemic limitations.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
This trade-off between whether an aim or group of aims is worthwhile or realisable runs in the other direction as well: perhaps, if our present condition were different, our current group of worthwhile aims can expand to include them as well.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
The most plausible objections are raised at how (a) cannot be satisfied by current rules proposed in (b), thus necessitating either the rejection and replacement of (b) with other rules, or how no possible or feasible rules can satisfy (a), necessitating the rejection and replacement of (a). This requires a fully different approach than with the REA and CEA, namely whether (a) is worthwhile and realisable and whether (a) is satisfied faster, easier and/or more reliably by (b) than alternative rules.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
As an illustration, it helps to first examine Popper&#39;s normative demarcation criteria: they are a consequence of accepting that past predictive success of a theoretical system is not indicative of truth. However, past predictive failure of a theoretical system is, so Popper claims, indicative of falsity somewhere in the theoretical system. If it is impossible to follow a methodological rule that rules on predictive success, such that increasing predictive success will aim at (probably approximately) true theories in the present, we must abandon or weaken our rule. But can we maintain weaker aims? So long as our aim remains directed at increasing truth content and directed away from increasing false content of theoretical systems and predictive failure is indicative of falsity, Popper suggests adopt the strictly weaker aim of minimising falsehood by taking predictive failure to be indicative of falsity of a theoretical system. This is because, although it is incredibly difficult, predictive failure remains indicative of falsity &lt;i&gt;somewhere&lt;/i&gt;, even if the falsity should be located in assessments of the experimental setup.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4 style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
3. Popper&#39;s methodological rules&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Before continuing on to the criticism leveled by Lakatos, Feyerabend and Kuhn, it helps to cover some of Popper&#39;s proposed methodological rules.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
(1) Scientists ought to prefer a new theoretical system (research programme, paradigm, ...) that has greater predictive content than its predecessors.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
This rule an expansion of Popper&#39;s (and Ayer and Carnap&#39;s) criterion of predictability of statements. We are no longer merely interested in which statements are empirically significant and which are not; now we are interested in which statements have greater empirical content compared to their rivals. The greater the empirical content the better.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
(2) Scientists ought to prefer a new theoretical system (research programme, paradigm, ...) that is of greater explanatory breadth and depth of preceding theoretical systems; that is, &#39;a theory that has been well corroborated can only be superseded by one of a higher level of universality&#39; (2002, 276).&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
(3) Scientists ought to test a theoretical system as severely as possible (&lt;i&gt;ibid.&lt;/i&gt; 281).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Note that Popper neglected the corollary of this rule which has similarities with argumentative norms: scientists ought to construct theories as &lt;i&gt;robust &lt;/i&gt;as possible, that is, the theory that is tested must be the &lt;i&gt;best available version&lt;/i&gt; of that theory. We are interested in testing &#39;mature&#39; scientific theories.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
On this point, Kuhn&#39;s work emphasising &#39;normal&#39; science does &lt;i&gt;improve&lt;/i&gt; on Popper&#39;s proposed methodological norms, although it is not at odds with Popper&#39;s norms. For the life of me, I cannot understand why some critics take the discussion between Kuhn and Popper to amount to more than a dispute over emphasis over the degree of the usefulness of &#39;normal&#39; science. While it is of use to construct &#39;mature&#39; scientific theories rather than &#39;immature&#39; theories, there exist diminishing returns, and it would be a mistake to &lt;i&gt;over&lt;/i&gt;emphasise its importance.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
(4) Scientists ought to reject theoretical systems that are incompatible with agreed-upon statements about some spatio-temporal location &lt;i&gt;K&lt;/i&gt; (i.e. if an epistemic community is in agreement that a theoretical system is incompatible with an observation or experimental result, one of the two must go; if the experimental result is accepted, some part of the theoretical system must go); we can only provisionally accept theoretical systems that have not been falsified.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
That is to say, Popper&#39;s much-maligned criterion of falsifiability for theoretical systems, although central to his territorial demarcation, is of far less importance in his normative criteria: sometimes the fault lies with the experimental setup, other times the fault lies with some core assumption, or with an auxiliary hypothesis. There is no way to determine this from the armchair. Sometimes it is a crossed wire; other times it is the entire theoretical scaffolding.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
However, Popper suggests that when rejecting the theoretical system [for it must be rejected as a whole], it must be replaced with a &#39;cousin&#39; or &#39;sister&#39; system that retains as much of its content as possible. The scientist&#39;s aim is to then retain as much content as possible without engaging in mutilation to key theoretical terms, introducing &lt;i&gt;ad hoc&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;explanations for incoherence or failure, and isolating parts of the theoretical system from one another as best as possible in order to check where the problem lies.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
(5) Scientists ought not accept inconsistent statements.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
(6) Each progressive theory &#39;contains the old, well corroborated theory--or at least a good approximation to it&#39; (276).&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
We can include a number of additional methodological norms, such as:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
(7) Scientists ought to prefer theoretically and conceptually simpler theoretical systems over their rivals.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
This rule is not emphasised as much as the other rules in &lt;i&gt;Logic&lt;/i&gt;, although it goes without saying that adopting it helps avoid the objection that predictive content can always be introduced by way of irrelevant conjunction.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4 style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
4. Finally, the nuanced objection&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Continuing this example, Lakatos may disagree with Popper and claim neither past predictive success or failure of theoretical systems is indicative of truth &lt;i&gt;or &lt;/i&gt;falsity. If so, Lakatos may change (a) to some related aim nearby to truth, or change (b) such that past predictive success or failure of research programmes is indicative of truth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
This particular type of criticism was developed by Feyerabend, Lakatos and implicitly by Kuhn: Popper&#39;s norms do not satisfy (a), therefore either better norms must replace Popper&#39;s or we adopt different (realisable) aims.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
It&#39;s worth reexamining what evidence Lakatos, Feyerabend and Kuhn presented against Popper&#39;s normative criteria. I will not do that here. Rather, I will jump to their conclusion, which amounted to the following: judged purely on a short-term, tactical level, (1)-(7) were violated when examining a number of historical case-studies, and at the time (or in retrospect) we were well-advised to break these rules. In short, &lt;i&gt;all these rules are too severe&lt;/i&gt;. In sum, adhering to these proposed rules too rigidly in the short-term goes against our long-term interest of (1).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Framed this way, much of the work done by Lakatos, Feyerabend, and Kuhn is almost trivially responded to by affirming the following thesis: short-term and long-term interests will almost always conflict in almost any (socially, conceptually, logically) complex, long-term (inter-generational) goal-directed activity.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
This thesis, I believe, is true for the following reason: there simply &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt; the constant tension between short-term and long-term interests in almost all social activities. If short-term interests are prioritised over long-term interests in times of war, to take one (unfortunate, but illustrative) example (or with chess), if the aim is to maximise immediate success with short-term tactics (e.g. immediately taking an open position) this will assuredly go against long-term strategy because there is no care taken to see whether taking the position will help achieve some long-term aim (such as winning a game of chess); if long-term interests are prioritised, long-term strategy is bound to clash with short-term tactics, since strategic rules will rigidly direct tactical decisions that are deleterious for some on the tactical level (e.g. a sacrificial rearguard to protect a withdrawal).&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Unlike chess (or even war), the natural sciences and other forms of empirical inquiry that involve inter-generational goal-directed activities (e.g. philosophy, politics, the social sciences, history, mathematics, etc.), are attempts at solving some of the most difficult, intractable and intransigent problems. It is natural that these sorts of problems involve some of the most complex, energy-exhaustive and time-intensive attempts at solving them, and are bound to include numerous historical case-studies that conflict with the overarching long-term goals. There will be dead-ends, moments that theory advances beyond available technology and searches for proverbial needles in haystacks.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
But if &amp;nbsp;the superior objection raised by Lakatos &lt;i&gt;et al&lt;/i&gt;. cannot undermine Popper&#39;s proposed normative rules, what can? I&#39;m writing up some notes on Feyerabend&#39;s proposed improvements to Popper&#39;s normative rules. They should be posted sometime in the upcoming weeks.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
Bibliography&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
Deutscher, M. (1968). &#39;Popper&#39;s Problem of an Empirical Base&#39;. &lt;i&gt;Australasian Journal of Philosophy&lt;/i&gt; 46: 277-288.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Pigliucci, M. &amp;amp; M. Boudry (2013). &lt;i&gt;Philosophy of Pseudoscience: Reconsidering the Demarcation Problem&lt;/i&gt;. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
Popper, K. (1935) [2002]. The Logic of Scientific Discovery. London: Routledge.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
11/8/17&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prognostic practitioners and transient underdetermination</title>
      <link>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/post/prognostic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/post/prognostic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
I wrote these notes on the problem of transient underdetermination in seventeenth century cosmology for a previous post on epistemic counter-closure, but the more I thought about it, the more I realised that it wasn&amp;rsquo;t an appropriate example: ever since Pierre Duhem, the cosmological dispute between heliocentric and geocentric models been historically understood in philosophy to primarily be a case of underdetermination rather than epistemic counter-closure. Introducing any instances of apparent inferential knowledge predicated on false basis beliefs produces additional confusion rather than clarity.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;
Setting the historical stage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to construct a label that accurately reflects the appropriate categories for these historical communities. It would be a-historical to label these individuals &amp;lsquo;scientists&amp;rsquo;: the relatively recent social community of scientists did not yet exist, since these individuals were, depending on where and when they lived, part-astrologer, astronomer, mathematician, engineer, cartographer and globe-maker. Furthermore, there is too much conceptual baggage carried over if these individuals were called &amp;lsquo;astrologers&amp;rsquo;, and &amp;lsquo;astronomer&amp;rsquo; obscures just as much as the label &amp;lsquo;astrologer&amp;rsquo;. However, their preferred titles of &amp;lsquo;mathematicus&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;astronomus&amp;rsquo; are more or less conceptually empty to the modern mind, carrying with them no baggage at all. Consequently, I have followed Robert Westman (2011) and decided to refer to these individuals as&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;prognostic practitioners&lt;/i&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the development of heliocentric models from the early twelfth century up to the mid-sixteenth and early seventeenth centuries: the twelfth-century prognosticator Alpetragius proposed in his &lt;i&gt;Kit?b f? l-hay?a&lt;/i&gt; an early heliocentric model, but insisted that it was at most a mathematical convenience, rather than a description of the physical world (Alpetragius? work was relatively popular in Europe, yet bore little similarities to later theories of heliocentrism beyond the central claim that the Earth orbited the Sun. See: Goldstein, 1964).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
At the time of the publication of Copernicus&amp;rsquo; &lt;i&gt;De revolutionibus&lt;/i&gt; in 1543, planetary tables such as Erasmus Reinold&amp;rsquo;s &lt;i&gt;Prutenic Tables&lt;/i&gt;, based on a heliocentric model, were no more accurate than star tables based on geocentric models found in Claudius Ptolemy&amp;rsquo;s &lt;i&gt;Almagest&lt;/i&gt;, published more than a thousand years previously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Furthermore, Copernicus&amp;rsquo; model suffered from the same problems that plagued Ptolemy&amp;rsquo;s geocentric model, namely the use of epicycles. That is to say, heliocentric models began as mathematical conveniences, and for a time continued to be little more than a mathematical convenience, for they were no more accurate in their predictions compared to geocentric and geoheliocentric models. Nor were they particularly simple in their construction, lacking the use of the ellipses to model planetary motion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
It was only at the time of Kepler&amp;rsquo;s publication in 1627 of the &lt;i&gt;Rudolphine Tables&lt;/i&gt;, based on Tycho Brahe&amp;rsquo;s data, that Kepler&amp;rsquo;s model of planetary motion was shown to better fit the astronomical evidence than planetary tables based on Ptolemy&amp;rsquo;s geocentric model. However, even Kepler&amp;rsquo;s elliptic heliocentric model provided only a rough approximation of the true orbit of planets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
To summarise the long and convoluted history of the development of heliocentrist models, over the course of a few hundred years, what began as a mathematical convenience soon developed into a realised theoretical system that, according to its adherents, described the physical structure of and natural laws governing the solar system. The model was smoothed out, simplified, and through its simplification became even more predicatively successful.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
This is an often-seen trend in the creation of mathematical or geometrical models: the model begins as a convenience, and after the model is repeatedly corroborated, revised and refined, the convenience is no longer &lt;i&gt;merely&lt;/i&gt; convenient, but, in the eyes of individuals that use the model, purportedly a mathematical reflection of the deeper structure of the world.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
A problem with this attempt at historical reconstruction: underdetermination&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
This reconstruction is, obviously, a fairly positive or Whiggish view of the historical development of a progressive research programme: the prognostic practitioners did not realise the value inherent in their model at its birth, grew to appreciate it for its elegance and mathematical simplicity compared to its rivals during its teenage years, and as it matured soon preferred it for a number of its theoretical virtues when compared to its rivals. At this point, the prognostic practitioners were like Eugene Winger (1960) or Hilary Putnam in their diagnosis of the state of play: these mathematical models were so &lt;i&gt;unreasonably effective&lt;/i&gt; that the best available explanation for their predictive success was that the model had captured some deeper structure of the world. Miracles don&amp;rsquo;t come easily.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
However, there is one issue that faces a reconstruction of the history of heliocentric models: there was a gradual increase in the confidence of prognostic practitioners in the predictive accuracy of Copernicus&amp;rsquo; heliocentric models compared to the rival Ptolemaic and Tychonic models, and a growing commitment to realism over instrumentalism or conventionalism by prognosticators. This is not in dispute. But this is a sociological phenomenon. However, even if the competing forms of heliocentrism were, after Kepler&amp;rsquo;s model was developed, generally more accurate in their predictions than Ptolemaic and Tychonic models, prognosticators were at this very time unable to account for a debilitating objection to heliocentric models: the confidence in heliocentric models existed&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;in despite of&lt;/i&gt; a defeating reason.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Consequently, we are faced with a puzzle: these prognosticators grew more confident in a research programme while at the same time the research programme faced a novel objection that had yet to be addressed, and could not be addressed with the available methods.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
As Tycho Brahe, perhaps the leading astronomer of his era, noted, if the Earth orbited the Sun, there would have been a measure of stellar parallax: at different times of the year, the stars would have slightly different positions. However, no change in their positions was measured by Brahe or, for that matter, any other astronomer until the nineteenth century.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In light of the failure to measure stellar parallax, it is worth reconstructing this motivation for the development of &lt;i&gt;geoheliocentric&lt;/i&gt; models. In order for heliocentric models of the solar system to be viable, heliocentrists had to introduce an auxiliary hypothesis: the stars were so far away as to prevent the measurement of stellar parallax.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
However, this auxiliary hypothesis that stars were necessarily remote to avoid any measurement of stellar parallax produced the &lt;i&gt;star size problem&lt;/i&gt;: the diameters measured of stars were, due to the methods used in the production of lenses in telescopes available at the time, as well as measurements taken by Brahe with the naked eye and the astronomer&amp;rsquo;s stave, did not reflect their true size. In fact, if heliocentrism were true and their available astronomical records were accepted, Procyon, one of Earth&amp;rsquo;s nearest stellar neighbours, would consequently dwarf the size of the Sun, extending in diameter to the orbit of Saturn around the Sun. Sirius would, in turn, dwarf Procyon.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
This exaggeration of their size meant that a heliocentrist was left with a conundrum: the local star, the Sun, was the only star in existence with a vastly smaller diameter when compared all other measured stars; all other stars were massive. The Sun would be a grain of sand in a universe full of pebbles and rocks. This conclusion was too absurd for Brahe, as well as other Tychonists and Ptolemacists: in order to fix the size of planets such that they were generally similar in size to the Sun, the stars would have to lie just beyond Saturn. With the stars fixed at this distance, the Sun was no longer an unexplained outlier; it was just one more grain of sand on a beach. As Albert van Helden says, &amp;lsquo;Tycho&amp;rsquo;s logic was impeccable; his measurements above reproach. A Copernican simply had to accept the results of this argument&amp;rsquo; (1985, 51).
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Consequently, Tycho and Nicholaus Reimers Baer both independently developed their rival geoheliocentric models. Under both Tychonism and Reimerism, the planets orbited the Sun, while the Sun orbited the Earth; the stars were situated beyond Saturn, and were a comparable size to the Sun. Procyon, for example, would be larger than Saturn, although slightly smaller than the Sun; Sirius would be larger than Procyon but slightly smaller than the Sun; and so on.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Since geoheliocentric models better accounted for the lack of measured stellar parallax, geoheliocentric prognosticators would (presumably) have stronger grounds for accepting realism than their heliocentric counterparts. While geoheliocentric models sacrificed simplicity in order to account for the lack of measured stellar parallax, elsewhere there were significant gains: there were no longer the debilitating objection of the Sun&amp;rsquo;s inexplicable deviance in size from the norm.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
One possible response to Brahe&amp;rsquo;s star-size problem would be to claim that this was merely an experimental monster that would be resolved with further developments of technology: the eye was simply not a reliable method for determining the relative size of distant stars: atmospheric refraction presumably distorted the size of each star, and astronomical prognosticators would have to wait for the development of more advanced methods, such as early telescopes. However, two generations after Brahe, Giovanni Battista Riccioli updated the star-size problem in his &lt;i&gt;Almagestum Novum&lt;/i&gt; (1651) to account for telescopes, noting that Galileo and Simon Marius&amp;rsquo; measurements of the size of stars were in agreement with Brahe&amp;rsquo;s (Graney &amp;amp; Grayson, 2011).
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The size of stars observed with either the naked eye or telescopes were similar&amp;ndash;that is, &lt;i&gt;similarly inaccurate&lt;/i&gt;. It was only until a century after Riccioli that in 1838, Friedrich Wilhem Bessel measured stellar parallax, providing an explanation for the illusory size of stars seen with the naked eye and early telescopes (Gingerich, 2011, 136).
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
A brief summary of the historical problem-situation&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The possibility space in the early seventeenth century was not limited to the previously mentioned models: the French mathematician Franois Vite&amp;rsquo;s unpublished manuscript, &lt;i&gt;Ad Harmonicum Coeleste Libri Quinque Priores&lt;/i&gt;, presents a model he dubbed &amp;lsquo;Francilinidean&amp;rsquo;. The model was &amp;lsquo;essentially Ptolemaic&amp;rsquo;, but departing &amp;lsquo;notably from Ptolemy&amp;rsquo; by replacing a number of Ptolemaic epicycles with &amp;lsquo;epi-ellipses and &lt;i&gt;elliptical deferents&lt;/i&gt;?&amp;lsquo;(Schofield 1965, 295 emphasis added).
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The manuscript is dated to approximately 1600-1603 (Swerdlow 1975, 188), almost a full decade before the publication of Kepler&amp;rsquo;s &lt;i&gt;Astronomia nova&lt;/i&gt; (1609), making it one of the earliest examples of a model that proposed an elliptical orbit of planetary motion. However, Francilinideanism, although existent within accessible possibility space, was apparently unknown to early seventeenth century prognosticators.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
There exist a number of other viable models, although they are more of historical curiosities: Martianus Capella proposed an early geoheliocentric model in the fourth century. Four centuries later, the Irish philosopher John Soctus Erigena proposed his own geoheliocentrist model that differed from Capella&amp;rsquo;s model in the number of planets that orbited the Sun. Kelallur Nilakantha Somayaji, an Indian prognosticator, may have developed another competing geoheliocentric theory that differed from both Reimers and Tycho (Ramasubramanian, 1994). These models existed within the accessible possibility space as well.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In sum, there were &lt;i&gt;at least&lt;/i&gt; six viable models of the solar system during the early seventeenth century: Keplerism, Copernicanism, Tychoism, Reimerism, Francilinideanism and Ptolemacism.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
There are a number of theoretical virtues we can choose to rank each model:
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Empirical fit: geoheliocentrists like Tychonicists and Reimerists, as well as geocentrists like Ptolemacists and Francilinideanists, could account for apparent (but ultimately erroneous) falsifiers for a theoretical system like the star-size problem, while heliocentrists like Copernicans and Keplerians could not.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Predictive accuracy: Kepleranism and Copernicanism were both far more predicatively accurate than their rivals, yet there was a trade-off for predictive accuracy of planetary motion: both models relied on rejecting the available empirical evidence as an experimental ?monster? that would be eventually resolved. Some early Copernicans, such as Christoph Rothmann and Philips Lansbergen, even answered the star-size problem by providing implausible theological arguments: they argued the size of all other stars was no problem, for God was not constrained in any way, and could choose to produce stars at any size he desired (Graney, 2013).
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Simplicity of the model: geoheliocentric models like Tychonism and Reimerism were preferable to geocentric models like Ptolemacism and Francilinideanism, since they were often a better fit to the experimental evidence, yet geocentric models like Ptolemacism, while less predicatively accurate, were simpler than geoheliocentric models: all planets and the Sun orbited the Earth under geocentric models, while under geoheliocentric models all planets orbited the Sun, while the Sun orbited the Earth.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Lastly, it is even possible to compare heliocentric, geoheliocentric and geocentric models with one another: for geoheliocentric models, Tychonism was a heliostatic theory: it posited that the Earth was stationary; Reimerism posited that the Earth rotated around its axis. Thus Reimerism accounted for some experimental results that supported the rotation of the Earth better than Tychonism, although Reimerism now appeared &lt;i&gt;ad hoc when&lt;/i&gt; compared to Tychonism, for it posited an absurdity that lead to Tycho developing his model as heliostatic: there was no available mathematical account for the movement of objects in space on a rotating Earth. As Ptolemy objected,
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;quote&gt;All objects not actually standing on the earth would appear to have the same motion, opposite to that of the earth: neither clouds nor other flying or thrown objects would ever be seen moving towards the east, since the earth&amp;rsquo;s motion towards the east would always outrun and overtake them, so that all other objects would seem to move in the direction of the west and the rear&amp;hellip; Yet we quite plainly see that they do undergo all these kinds of motion, in such a way that they are not even slowed down or speeded up at all by any motion of the earth.&lt;/quote&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
For geocentric models such as Francilinideanism, since it relied on elliptical orbits and eliminated epicycles, it was preferable to Ptolemacism on grounds of mathematical and conceptual simplicity, as well as predictive accuracy, for it was empirically equivalent to Kepler&amp;rsquo;s model; for heliocentric models, Kepleranism was preferable to Copernicanism on these same grounds of predictive accuracy and simplicity.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Depending on whichever theoretical virtue a prognostic practitioner preferred over its rivals, there were eminently plausible grounds for preferring and dispreferring any model. It was only with a theoretical backing for the mathematical laws that governed the movement of planets that would not be available until the publication of Newton&amp;rsquo;s &lt;i&gt;Principia&lt;/i&gt; (1687) that an account for Kepler&amp;rsquo;s theory of elliptical heliocentrism had the requisite geometrical backing, as well as a viable alternative physics that unified planetary and terrestrial motion to rival Aristotelian physics.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
However, Newtonian mechanics as it is taught today, reflecting more of the formulations set out by Laplace and Langrange, bears little resemblance to &lt;i&gt;Isaac Newton&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/i&gt; mechanics. As the physicist Steven Weinberg said, &amp;lsquo;Newton is pre-Newtonian&amp;rsquo;. Even the theoretical grounds for adopting heliocentricism were subject to centuries-long game of conceptual elimination, addition and reconstruction, for Newton&amp;rsquo;s mechanical theory lacked any &lt;i&gt;physical&lt;/i&gt; explanation for the movement of planets.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
Examining the philosophical problem-situation&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(We have, unsurprisingly, a case of Arrow&amp;rsquo;s impossibility theorem in action: there were upwards of six distinct alternative models and at least three different desirable theoretical virtues for each model (simplicity, predictive accuracy, empirical fit). Ranking preferences for each model based on a &lt;i&gt;Borda Count&lt;/i&gt;, for example, in which there are $n$ models, and based on a criterion $C$, the best model is given $n$ points, the second-best $n$1 points, and so on, isn&amp;rsquo;t available, since it violates a central assumption in Arrow&amp;rsquo;s theorem, the assumption of &lt;i&gt;binary independence&lt;/i&gt;. This leads to the result that the prognosticatory community necessarily could not rationally decide on a ranking of models. Davide Rizza (2014) shows that even weakening binary independence cannot salvage theory-choice.)
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;This is but a rediscovery of the problem that was first acknowledged in the fifth century B.C.E by Apollonius and Hipparchus: the models of the Sun&amp;rsquo;s motion, the simple eccentric and epicycle-deferent, were geometrically equivalent. In 1543, a thousand years later, the very same problem was acknowledged by Copernicus: &amp;lsquo;It makes no difference that what they [the ancients] explain by a resting Earth and a universe whirling round, we take up in the opposite way so that together with them we might rush to the same goal. For in such matters, those things that are thus mutually related agree, in turn, one with the other&amp;rsquo; (Westman 2011, 5).
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
These differing models were themselves (more or less) empirically equivalent, and geometrically transformable from one to another, taking different equants at the point of orbit and introducing or eliminating epicycles as necessary to maintain equivalence. Thus there would have to be &lt;i&gt;different&lt;/i&gt; grounds for theory-preference besides empirical fit, but no model was obviously preferable when compared to its rivals due to Arrow&amp;rsquo;s theorem. Furthermore, even if one model had been preferable compared to all available rival models, the question arises whether the proposed criteria for theory-preference itself were suitable.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
While the standards adopted today pay far more attention to empirical and logical grounds (i.e. empirical adequacy, predictive success, coherence, amongst others), this papers over the previously accepted epistemic conventions of sixteenth and seventeenth-century prognosticators: this was a time that a criterion of knowledge was inexorably tied to coherence with Biblical exegesis and the writings of the Ancients. Rothmann and Lansbergen&amp;rsquo;s appeal to the extra-natural power of God may be absurd to the modern-day way of thinking, but it was not outside the realm of acceptability to prognosticators. It is only in hindsight and several hundred years of cultural shift that the plausibility of a standard wanes. Consider the counterfactual: had history run a different course, Biblical authority may have been an overwhelmingly strong standard compared to other theoretical virtues, leading to an outcome in which prognosticators preferred geocentric models over their rivals, even if geocentric models were less predicatively successful. In sum, the very criteria for theory-preference may be historically contingent.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
What would have been the most epistemically prudent action, given this case of transient underdetermination?
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In this historical case-study, as with many examples from the history of science, heliocentric, geoheliocentric and geocentric prognosticators more often than not genuinely believed their theoretical system accurately reflected a deeper structure of the cosmos. However, this genuine belief was, in almost all cases, in error.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Instead, for the modern-day anti-realist, the diagnosis is obvious: it would have been more appropriate to adopt a form of Alpetragius&amp;rsquo;s conventionalism. Some prognostic practitioners took this route:
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Andreas Osiander&amp;rsquo;s claimed in his preface to Copernicus&amp;rsquo; &lt;i&gt;De revolutionibus&lt;/i&gt; that a heliocentric model was merely a useful method, and &amp;lsquo;need not be true nor even probable&amp;ndash;if they provide a calculus consistent with the observations, that alone is enough&amp;rsquo; (Copernicus, 1992; cf. Gingerich, 2004).
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Giovanni Giovano Pontano concluded, &amp;lsquo;The circles, the epicycles, and all suppositions of this sort should, therefore, be regarded as imaginary; they have no real existence in the heavens. They have been invented and imagined so as to let the celestial motions be grasped and to exhibit them to our sight&amp;rsquo; (Duhem, 1969, 55).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Cardinal Bellarmine claimed that Copernican theory produced a helpful and useful calculating device that can be used to &amp;lsquo;save the appearances&amp;rsquo; and nothing more, for &amp;lsquo;[t]o demonstrate that the appearances are saved by assuming the sun is at the center and the earth is in the heavens is not the same thing as to demonstrate that in fact the sun is in the center and the earth is in the heavens&amp;rsquo; (Drake 1957, 162-4).
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In fact, as Gingerich notes, &amp;lsquo;nearly every sixteenth-century astronomer accepted Copernicus&amp;rsquo;s &lt;i&gt;De revolutionibus&lt;/i&gt; as an up-to-date recipe book for computing positions of planets, but definitely not as a description of physical reality? [since] the idea of a spinning Earth was completely ridiculous&amp;rsquo; (2011, 135-140). A conventionalist or instrumentalist would retroactively diagnose the problem as follows: past prognosticators did in fact or ought to have emulated Alpetragius, Osiander and Bellarmine, but spoke out of turn, for they were unreasonably optimistic. The conclusion (presumably) is inescapable: &lt;i&gt;the historical data compels us to conclude that future scientists ought to be scientific anti-realists&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h3&gt;
Blake, R. (1960). Theory of Hypothesis among Renaissance Astronomers, in Blake, Ducasse, and Madden, eds., &lt;i&gt;Theories of Scientific Method: The Renaissance Through the Nineteenth Century.&lt;/i&gt; Seattle: University of Washington Press.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Bradley, J. (1727-1728). An account of a new-discovered motion of the fixed stars. &lt;i&gt;Philosophical Transactions&lt;/i&gt; 32, 637-61.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Copernicus, N. (1992). &lt;i&gt;On the Revolutions. Translation and Commentary&lt;/i&gt; by Edward Rosen. Baltimore, MD &amp;amp; London: The Johns Hopkins University Press.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Drake, S. (1957). Bellarmine to Foscarini, 12 April 1615, &lt;i&gt;Opere&lt;/i&gt;, National Edition, ed. Antonio Favaro, 12, 171-2; from &lt;i&gt;Discoveries and Opinions of Galileo&lt;/i&gt;, trans. Stillman Drake. Garden City: Doubleday.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Duhem, P. (1969). &lt;i&gt;To Save the Phenomena: An Essay on the Idea of Physical Theory from Plato to Galileo&lt;/i&gt;, Chicago: University of Chicago Press, excerpted from Giovanni Gioviano Pontano, &lt;i&gt;De rebus coelestibus&lt;/i&gt;, libri xiv.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Gingerich, O. (2004). &lt;i&gt;The Book Nobody Read&lt;/i&gt;. Walker Books.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
______. (2011). Galileo, the impact of the telescope, and the birth of modern astronomy. &lt;i&gt;Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society&lt;/i&gt;. 155(2).
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Goldstein, B.R. (1964). On the theory of Trepidation according to Th?bit b.Qurra and al-Zarq?llu and Its Implications for Homocentric Planetary Theory, &lt;i&gt;Centaurus&lt;/i&gt;, 10: 232-247.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Graney, C.M. &amp;amp; T.P. Grayson. (2011). &amp;lsquo;On the telescopic discs of stars&amp;ndash; a review and analysis of stellar observations from the early 17th through the middle 19th centuries&amp;rsquo;, &lt;i&gt;Annals of science&lt;/i&gt;, lxviii: 351-73.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Graney, C.M. (2013). &amp;lsquo;Stars as the armies of God: Lansbergen&amp;rsquo;s incorporation of Tycho Brahe&amp;rsquo;s star-size argument into the Copernican theory&amp;rsquo;, &lt;i&gt;Journal for the History of Astronomy&lt;/i&gt;, xliv.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
______. (2015). &lt;i&gt;Setting Aside All Authority: Giovanni Battisa Riccioli and the Science against Copernicus in the Age of Galileo&lt;/i&gt;, Notre Dame, Indiana: University of Notre Dame Press.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
van Helden, A. (1985). &lt;i&gt;Measuring the universe&lt;/i&gt;. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Ramasubramanian, K., M.D. Srinivas &amp;amp; M.S. Sriram (1994). Modification of an earlier Indian planetary theory by the Kerala astronomers (cf. 1500 AD) and the implied heliocentric picture of planetary motion. &lt;i&gt;Current Science&lt;/i&gt;. 66(1).
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Rizza, D. (2014). Arrow&amp;rsquo;s theorem and theory choice. &lt;i&gt;Synthese&lt;/i&gt;, 191(8): 1847-1856.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Schofield, C. (1965.) The Geoheliocentric mathematical hypothesis in sixteenth-century planetary theory, &lt;i&gt;The British Journal for the History of Science&lt;/i&gt;. 2(8).
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Swerdlow, N.M. (1975). The planetary theory of Franois Vite. &lt;i&gt;Journal for the History of Astronomy&lt;/i&gt;. vi, 185-208.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Westman, R.S. (2011). &lt;i&gt;The Copernican Question: Prognostication, Skepticism, and Celestial Order&lt;/i&gt;. Berkeley: University of California Press.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Winger, E. (1960). The unreasonable effectiveness of mathematics in the natural sciences. &lt;i&gt;Communications in Pure and Applied Mathematics&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;13(1).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One version of the pessimistic meta-induction is self-undermining</title>
      <link>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/publication/pessimisticmetainduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/publication/pessimisticmetainduction/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Return of a Demarcation Problem</title>
      <link>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/talk/demarcationproblem/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/talk/demarcationproblem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A previous version of this talk was presented at the Triennial International Conference of the Italian Society for Logic and the Philosophy of Science at University of Bologna on Aug 23, 2017. The website is available &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.silfs.it/silfs-2017-home/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another version of this talk was presented at the Nordic Network for Philosophy of Science at University of Copenhagen on April 19, 2017. The website is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://nnpscience.wordpress.com/meetings/copenhagen-2017/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A later version of this talk was presented at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kcl.ac.uk/artshums/depts/philosophy/research/seminars/seminars/advanced.aspx&#34;&gt;Advanced Research Seminar&lt;/a&gt; at King&amp;rsquo;s College London.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An objection from intuition or normal use of terms</title>
      <link>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/post/normaluse/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/post/normaluse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;tr_bq&#34; style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
This form of intuitionism is, in part, the guiding principle seen in, for example, &amp;lsquo;common sense&amp;rsquo; theories, such as folk psychology, folk physics, &amp;lsquo;common sense&amp;rsquo; realism and intuitive correspondence theories (although &amp;lsquo;common sense&amp;rsquo; realism and correspondence theories are, in virtue of being defensible philosophical theories, rather than indefensible empirical theories, on far surer footing than either folk psychology and folk physics). Such commonsensicalism is designed to protect major revision to our way of seeing the world, our&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Weltanschauung.&lt;/i&gt; In small amounts it&amp;rsquo;s good to heed this call to refrain from unprompted and unnecessary revision; I argue in its more general form it is false; more specifically, it&amp;rsquo;s often the intellectual scaffolding that holds up the objection from ill-fit, and directed at demarcation criteria that do not fully cohere to our intuitive conception of what statements are empirically significant.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
There exists tension between the proposed amendment or revision to a community&amp;rsquo;s intuitions or commonplace ways of speaking [call that proposed amendment an explication, or &lt;i&gt;E&lt;/i&gt;] and the intuitive concepts or ways of speaking [call these &lt;i&gt;I&lt;/i&gt;].&amp;nbsp;We are left with a disjunction &amp;nbsp;[&lt;i&gt;E&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color: white;&#34;&gt;?&lt;i&gt;I&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color: white;&#34;&gt;], the acceptance of &lt;i&gt;I&lt;/i&gt;, and the rejection of &lt;i&gt;E&lt;/i&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;But why not reason differently to the conclusion that a community&amp;rsquo;s intuitive concepts or ways of speaking are mistaken? Under what conditions it would be appropriate to reject &lt;i&gt;I&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;and accept &lt;i&gt;E&lt;/i&gt;?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
In section 1, I cover one objection from ill-fit, that is, to accept &lt;i&gt;I&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;and reject &lt;i&gt;E&lt;/i&gt;. In sections 2-2.3 I set out general reasons to accept &lt;i&gt;I&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;and reject &lt;i&gt;E&lt;/i&gt;. Section 3 addresses how under what conditions the apparent conservatism when faced with conceptual underdetermination may lead to minor concept-revision. Lastly, in section 4 I show how it is appropriate to reject &lt;i&gt;I&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;and accept E&lt;i&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;in the case I am most concerned with, &lt;i&gt;viz&lt;/i&gt;. the objection from ill-fit is not appropriate when applied to explications of intuitive concepts about which sentences fall on either side of proposed demarcation criteria.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
1. The objection from ill-fit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;
Imagine how the following story must play out to from a linguistic community&amp;rsquo;s point of view: a philosopher declares to the community a certain form of longstanding activity or a way of conceptualising the world and our place within it, as well as our entrenched forms of discourse, as fundamentally&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;mistaken&lt;/i&gt;. What&amp;rsquo;s more, the philosopher has arrived at this conclusion through the employment of armchair philosophical introspection: they yield only&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;theory&lt;/i&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Consider the two following examples: the Buddhist philosopher N?g?rjuna&amp;nbsp;may find a small following after presenting the idea that language &lt;i style=&#34;font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;qua &lt;/i&gt;language fundamentally mismatches the world, that a number of apparently pertinent questions are nothing but a category mistake, and we must do away with these questions. N?g?rjuna may be interpreted as advocating a form of quietism, and subsequently we ought to &amp;lsquo;reject commitment to some or perhaps even all kinds of entities by adopting a type of &lt;i&gt;pretense&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;or &lt;i&gt;make&lt;/i&gt;-&lt;i&gt;believe&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;stance&amp;hellip; all without exception is conceptual construction; in other words, even allegedly ultimately real entities are themselves just conveniently established fictions&amp;rsquo; (Priest, 2011, 144).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Some corollaries within Buddhist traditions (such as N?g?rjuna&amp;rsquo;s development of the Madhyamaka school) may be found in Rudolf Carnap&amp;rsquo;s own arguments for metaphysical deflationism and a deflationary theory of truth (Tanaka, 2014; Priest &lt;i&gt;et al.&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;2011; Finnigan, 2011), and there will be a small number of Carnapians that accept his arguments: &amp;lsquo;truth is truth within a framework; the ultimate truth is that nothing is &lt;i&gt;really&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;true (i.e., true in virtue of some real, intrinsic properties that are independent of frameworks)&amp;rsquo; (Priest, 2011, 145).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
However, after the discussion has (provisionally) settled, the conclusion usually drawn by the wider linguistic community is usually that &lt;i&gt;this form of radical conceptual or linguistic revision is out of place&lt;/i&gt;. Why is that?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Focusing on a specific issue of intransigence within the philosophical community, this commonsensicalism is the skeletal structure holding up a common reply to the demarcationist programme, specifically that the demarcationist has mangled certain concepts or ways of speaking such that they bear little similarity to their pre-theoretic use. This leads to giving far more weight to intuitions or ways of speaking over any attempt to clarify or explicate certain concepts: if there exists tension, the wider community will generally find that fau&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;lt will invariably lie with the renegade philosopher, and like&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;N?g?rjuna&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;and Carnap&amp;rsquo;s dismissal of ways of speaking, a relatively small number of members of the community will be convinced of the arguments in favour of demarcation (although in this instance, there is the fine line to be drawn between arguing in favour of revision of our concepts and claiming that these concepts accurately describe the feature of the world).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;For example,&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt; Popper (1959, 65-66; cf. 95) says that in order to be empirically significant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;tr_bq&#34; style=&#34;font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;?&amp;hellip; the theory [must] allow us to deduce, roughly speaking, more empirical singular statements than we can deduce from the initial conditions alone. ? A theory is to be called [empirically significant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;] if it divides the class of all possible basic statements unambiguously into the follow two non-empty subclasses. First, the class of all those basic statements with which it is inconsistent (or which it rules out, or prohibits): we call the the class of the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-style: italic; vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;potential falsifiers &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;of the theory; and secondly, the class of those basic statement which it does not contradict (or which it ?permits?). We can put this more briefly by saying: a theory is [empirically significant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;] if the class of its potential falsifiers is not empty?. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;However, this conception of empirical significance excludes isolated existential statements of the form &amp;lsquo;There exists an &lt;i&gt;X&lt;/i&gt;&amp;rsquo;. P&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;opper&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt; (&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;1959, 94-95, 101; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;1983, 161&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt; provides a numbe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;r of motivating reasons to adopt a way of speaking that treats isolated existential statements as empirically non-significant, but my interest here is not to cover these reasons. Rather, my interest is the diagnosis of the commonsensical attitude that permits trumping this proposed revision to pre-theoretical conceptual schema by an appeal to present practices and intuition.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit; font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;For one example of this commonsensicalism in action, Kneale (1974, 207) objects to Popper&amp;rsquo;s criterion of demarcation on the following grounds:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&amp;lsquo;there is a strange departure from the ordinary use of words in maintaining that hypotheses of natural law are empirical, because they are open to refutation by experience, while denying that [isolated] existential statements can ever deserve the same title. ? Indeed, if the word &amp;ldquo;empirical&amp;rdquo; is to be applied at all to propositions&amp;hellip; , there is a much better case for applying it to those which may be &lt;i&gt;established&lt;/i&gt; empirically than for applying it to those which may be &lt;i&gt;refuted&lt;/i&gt; empirically&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit; font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit; font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;Kneale&amp;rsquo;s argument shares some affinities with a Moorean argument: Popper claims to revise our conceptual categories, but the revision is on the face of it absurd. Rather, we must look at Popper&amp;rsquo;s conclusion (i.e. we must no longer treat isolated existential statements as empirically significant) as &lt;i&gt;itself&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;a &lt;i&gt;reductio&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;of his project, rather than taking Popper&amp;rsquo;s arguments to effectively undercut our intuitive concepts.&amp;nbsp;Consequently Kneale can reject Popper&amp;rsquo;s attempt at revision.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit; font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit; font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;Consequently, the community&amp;rsquo;s intuitions regarding empirical significance and the acceptability of demarcation criteria are at odds with one another: intuition and common use rules &lt;i&gt;in&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;treating isolated existential statements as empirically significant; the proposed criterion rule &lt;i&gt;out&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;treating isolated existential statements as empirically significant. What plausible rational reconstruction of the motivations for the community&amp;rsquo;s objection would provide reason for rejecting the demarcationist project?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit; font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit; font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;As Carnap (1961, v.) recognises, concept-revision occurs, if not by fiat, then by other means, namely (to use his earlier terminology, &amp;lsquo;rational reconstruction&amp;rsquo;): &amp;lsquo;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit; text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;The old concepts did not ordinarily originate by way of deliberate formulation, but in more or less unreflected and spontaneous development. The new definitions should be superior to the old in clarity and exactness, and, above all, should fit into a systematic structure of concepts. Such a clarification of concepts, nowadays frequently called ?explication?, still seems to me one of the most important tasks of philosophy, especially if it is concerned with the main categories of human thought&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit; font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit; text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit; font-weight: normal;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit; text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;But it cannot possibly be, as Carnap writes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: start;&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;in his &amp;lsquo;Intellectual Autobiography&amp;rsquo;: &amp;lsquo;Although I was guided in my procedure by the psychological facts concerning the formation of concepts of material things out of perceptions, my real aim was not the description of this genetic process, but rather its rational reconstruction - i.e., a schematized description of an imaginary procedure, consisting of rationally prescribed steps,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;text-align: start;&#34;&gt;which would lead to essentially the same results as the actual psychological process&amp;rsquo;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-align: start;&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;(1963,&amp;nbsp;15; italics added). The very issue of Popper&amp;rsquo;s criterion producing fundamentally different results than in Kneale&amp;rsquo;s intuition&amp;ndash;the two are not one in the same.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;2. Intuitions, everyday use, and avoidance of concept change&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;
One common form of reasoning that motivates raising objections from ill-fit is as follows: no one would dispute that epistemic and linguistic communities have certain pre-theoretical intuitions about how the world hangs together and our place and relationship within it&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;. There is a &amp;lsquo;folk-cosmology&amp;rsquo; in play, what we can call an &lt;i&gt;intuitive conceptual scheme&lt;/i&gt;. We can call this form of commonsensicalism a form of &lt;i&gt;intuitionism&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;Or, if we wish to be approach this objection differently, without an appeal to our pre-theoretical intuitions, we use certain terms in everyday discourse in ways that are not in dispute, ways of speaking that are entrenched within our interaction with one another. We can call this form of commonsensicalism&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;natural language philosophy&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;I&lt;/span&gt;f a philosopher should attempt to revise a community&amp;rsquo;s intuitive conceptual scheme or assert that a community change their use of entrenched terms, on what grounds should we take their proposal for a revision seriously? These sorts of things aren&amp;rsquo;t open to revision simply by &lt;i&gt;fiat&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
This formation bears some similarities to the much earlier paradox of analysis, known since &lt;a href=&#34;https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/analysis/s6.html#4&#34;&gt;Plato&amp;rsquo;s &lt;i&gt;Meno&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. To summarise Michael Beaney&amp;rsquo;s gloss, consider an analysis of the form &amp;lsquo;&lt;i&gt;A&lt;/i&gt; is &lt;i&gt;B&lt;/i&gt;&amp;rsquo; where &lt;i&gt;A&lt;/i&gt; is the &lt;i&gt;analysandum&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;(what is analysed) and &lt;i&gt;C&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;the &lt;i&gt;analysans &lt;/i&gt;(what is offered as the analysis). Either &amp;lsquo;&lt;i&gt;A&lt;/i&gt;&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;&lt;i&gt;C&lt;/i&gt;&amp;rsquo; have the same meaning, thus analysis expresses a triviality, or they do not, and in which the &lt;i&gt;analysans&lt;/i&gt; is incorrect. Subsequently, no analysis can be both correct and informative.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
In this case (following Carnap, 1956, 8-9), any case of explication of the form &amp;lsquo;&lt;i&gt;D&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;is &lt;i&gt;in fact&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;E&lt;/i&gt;&amp;rsquo; where &amp;lsquo;&lt;i&gt;D&lt;/i&gt;&amp;rsquo; is the &lt;i&gt;explicandum&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;(what is explained), the intuitive conceptual scheme, and &amp;lsquo;&lt;i&gt;E&lt;/i&gt;&amp;rsquo; the &lt;i&gt;explicatum&lt;/i&gt; (what is offered as the explanation), the proposed revision or clarification of intuitive concepts. An explication &lt;i&gt;qua &lt;/i&gt;explication must reveal something different than what was expected, otherwise the explicandum and explicatum are identical, and thus uninformative. But on what grounds should a community accept the explicatum when it differs from the explicandum? (Carnap himself recognised this similarity with the paradox of analysis: see&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;ibid.&lt;/i&gt;, 8, fn7.)&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
There is an intui&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;tively good reason for the &lt;i&gt;prima facie &lt;/i&gt;continuity of an intuitive conceptual scheme when faced with proposed revisions. What is in play is close to&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt; what Quine (1990, 14) called the &amp;lsquo;maxim of minimum mutilation&amp;rsquo;: it is reasonable not to alter or discard theories unless there is a positive reason to do so. This same principle must hold for a community&amp;rsquo;s intuitive conceptual scheme and ways of speaking&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;2.1 The avoidance of potential error&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;What motivates accepting the maxim of minimum &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;mutilation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit; white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;? &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;docs-internal-guid-57509d64-1441-2488-b7d1-41251976b3f3&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;vertical-align: baseline;&#34;&gt;We can think of this avoidance of unnecessary change in the following way: Darrell Rowbottom notes that virtue is, in part, &amp;lsquo;&lt;i&gt;linked to avoidance of error&lt;/i&gt;&amp;rsquo; (2001, 151f.). Untested change is inherently risky. In this sense, the institutional virtue practiced by the community is, in the words of Horace, &lt;i&gt;virtus est vitium fugere&amp;ndash;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;lsquo;Virtue is to escape vice&amp;rsquo; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Epistles&lt;/i&gt;, I, i, 41.)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: pre-wrap;&#34;&gt;&amp;ndash;or &amp;lsquo;error&amp;rsquo;, as the word &lt;i&gt;vitium&lt;/i&gt; can be translated (Sng, 2010, 6). The community practices restraint by adopting a principled course of action that has the lowest known likelihood of committing future error: the refusal to entertain other conceptual schemes unless there exists defeating evidence for the current conceptual scheme.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;2.2 An analogy between social, economic and philosophic problems of tacit knowledge&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
There are other motivating reasons as well, some that are more clearly pragmatic than epistemic, but both linked to the avoidance of unnecessary change as being &lt;i&gt;risk-adverse&lt;/i&gt;: t&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;his declaration of immediate displeasure with concept revision is, in virtue of being a motivation for adopting certain arguments, and not itself an argument, more of an attitude or way of seeing the world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;For the commonsensicalist, is not unlike a Burkeian attitude of preferring tr&lt;/span&gt;adition for tradition&amp;rsquo;s sake; or to make a more recent example, the community is, like how Michael Oakeshott describes the default state of a community, in a current state of affairs, and do not know what will happen to them if they should drastically change their way of life. &lt;i&gt;We&lt;/i&gt; are, in Oakeshott&amp;rsquo;s words &lt;i&gt;sentimentalists&lt;/i&gt;, even if the current state of affairs is not particularly well-suited for our living arrangements: it is far more likely that things will go worse than get better, and even if things should improve, there is something desirable about our current state of affairs in virtue of being in this state of affairs.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Related to that attitude of social conservatism is the more methodological Hayekian form of reasoning for resisting unnecessary change. This form of reasoning doesn&amp;rsquo;t forbid any and all conceptual change, but only unnecessary change brought forward from individuals that claim some special knowledge: a community&amp;rsquo;s social institutions have undergone proliferation and selective retention, and even if we are incapable of understanding what purpose they presently serve, we should be wary of the wholesale revision of social institutions on the basis of &lt;i&gt;a priori&lt;/i&gt; reasoning. Reasoning from first principles cannot take into account the tacit knowledge dispersed within the members of the community, and therefore will almost certainly produce unforeseen and undesirable consequences. Analogously, we should be doubly wary of any revision of concepts if the reasoning given for abandoning pre-theoretical intuitions rests solely on philosophical speculation.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Given the similarities between these conservative attitudes within the social, conceptual and linguistic realms, the claim is that philosophers simply lack the requisite grounds for introducing any top-down and wholesale revision to our concepts without first demonstrating the resilience of the theory that motivated concept-change.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
However, the theory is not resilient &lt;i&gt;because &lt;/i&gt;it mangles intuitive concepts. Hence, following this reasoning, there can be no concept-change directed by the authority of a philosophical &amp;lsquo;expert&amp;rsquo; that is not glacial in its movements, until this form of speaking has entrenched itself within the wider community. Perhaps, given enough time, the wider community will be not unlike the M?dhyamika philosophers, or Carnapian, or Popperian, in important respects to their conceptual schema, but until then, they are relegated to serving as an interesting, but ultimately unconvincing approach.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
(Of course, the whole issue is problematic, for if one were to ask why these approaches appear unconvincing, the reason given, more often than not, is psychologistic, sociological or linguistic, that is, it violates intuition or common use: it goes against common sense. The reasoning is entirely circular, and apparently a form of &lt;i&gt;vicious&lt;/i&gt; circularity. And yet this same appeal to common sense prevents adopting wholesale viewpoints that are rightly considered to be not just outlandish but patently false! The circular reasoning of the larger community appears, at least before further conceptual analysis, from one end vicious [especially in the eyes of the minority] and from the other perfectly respectable to both the majority and minority [the minority does not, after all, accept &lt;i&gt;every&lt;/i&gt; minority viewpoint]!)&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;2.3 Undue complexity, conceptual gerrymandering and &lt;i&gt;ad hoc&lt;/i&gt; reasoning&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;There are additional metaphors drawn from the risk-adverse attitudes towards unnecessary concept-change, such as Neurath&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;ship; a related metaphor is found in Procrustes&amp;rsquo; bed: take, as an illustration, what Robert Nozick writes in the preface to&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Anarchy, State and Utopia&lt;/i&gt;:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;tr_bq&#34;&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&amp;lsquo;One form of philosophical activity feels like pushing and shoving things to fit into some fixed perimeter of specified shape. All those things are lying out there, and they must be fit in. You push and shove the material into the rigid area getting it into the boundary on one side, and it bulges out on another. You run around and press in the protruding bulge, producing yet another in another place. So you push and shove and clip off corners from the things so they&amp;rsquo;ll fit and you press in until finally almost everything sits unstably more or less in there; what doesn&amp;rsquo;t get heaved&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;far&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;away so that it won&amp;rsquo;t be noticed. (Of course, it&amp;rsquo;s not all&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;that&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;crude. There&amp;rsquo;s also the coaxing and cajoling. And the body English.)&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Quickly&lt;/i&gt;, you find an angle from which it looks like an exact fit and take a snapshot; at a fast shutter speed before something else budges out too noticeably. Then, back to the darkroom to touch up the rents, rips, and tears in the fabric of the perimeter. All that remains is to publish the photograph as a representation of exactly how things are, and to note how nothing fits properly into any other shape&amp;rsquo; (Nozick, 1980, xiii).&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
I don&amp;rsquo;t dispute what Nozick says here, and I think more often than not, it is appropriate to side on behalf of tradition. If we are to be risk-adverse, it is better to uphold Quine&amp;rsquo;s maxim of minimum mutilation. Drastic changes to a conceptual scheme will have unforeseen conceptual consequences (analogous to Hayek&amp;rsquo;s economic concerns), leading to the results detailed by Nozick: the unforeseen butchery of concepts.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
But under what conditions can explication of concepts or modes of speech replace an intuitive conceptual scheme? Specifically, are there any set of circumstances that would lead an individual that presented the objection from ill-fit as recognising the appropriate replacement of a deficient intuitive conceptual scheme about the limits of empirical inquiry? Gradual replacement of a conceptual schema naturally occurs within communities, that is not in dispute. But is there a way to set out whether the community should seek to expedite the replacement of intuitive concepts in fields outside the natural sciences?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
3. The differences between philosophy and natural sciences&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;background-color: white; color: #181818; line-height: 21px; margin-bottom: 15px; padding: 0px;&#34;&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
One obvious objection to intuitionism and natural language philosophy is that there lacks some grand lineage to common sense or common use: they are &lt;i&gt;themselves&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;a form of theoretical reasoning, its&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;elf adopted surreptitiously by the community over the course of generations. Dan Dennett provides the objection as follows: &amp;lsquo;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;There is no such thing as philosophy-free science; there is only science whose philosophical baggage is taken on board without examination&amp;rsquo; (Dennett, 1995, 21).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color: white; color: #222222;&#34;&gt;Or take what John Maynard Keynes says about economic theory:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color: white; color: #222222;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;tr_bq&#34;&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color: white; color: #222222;&#34;&gt;The ideas of economists and political philosophers, both when they are right and when they are wrong, are more powerful than is commonly understood. Indeed the world is ruled by little else. Practical men, who believe themselves to be quite exempt from any intellectual influence, are usually the slaves of some defunct economist.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color: white; color: #222222;&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;Madmen in authority, who hear voices in the air, are distilling their frenzy from some academic scribbler of a few years back.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color: white; color: #222222;&#34;&gt;&amp;nbsp;(Keynes, 1936, 383-384)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
While it may be appropriate to retain intuitive concepts or natural language when not presented with defeating evidence, revision, even in the short term, is not impossible: if there exists defeating evidence that is not explicable according to the present conceptual scheme, intuitive concepts must fall by the wayside. For example, as Carnap (1962, section 3) notes, ?The prescientific term ?fish? was meant in about the sense of ?animal living in water?, while the zooligists? explicatum means ?animals which live in water, are cold-blooded vertebrates, and have gills throughout life??.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;We therefore have at least some idea of what instigates conceptual change: defeating reasons, more often than not defeating reasons that involve some form of empirical evidence. Outside the empirical sciences, in which empirical evidence does not play a role, there are, presumably, other ways to present defeating evidence. One obvious example is by &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;reductio ad absurdum&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;, which works within the conceptual framework to show its deficiencies compared to other frameworks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;: either the intuitive conceptual scheme leads to absurdity or &lt;/span&gt;contradiction&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;So we have our two-step process: first, for any successful argument for the abandonment of the intuitive concept that isolated existential statements &lt;i&gt;must&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;be empirically significant, we set out ways in which the conceptual scheme leads to undesirable consequences, that is, absurdity or contradiction. Second, any elucidation of a replacement conceptual scheme must present itself as sharing enough commonalities to the rejected scheme, as well as satisfying a number of desirable features.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: &amp;quot;times new roman&amp;quot;;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
According to Carnap (1962, 7), any criterion of empirical significance should be similar to the intuitive concept, precise, fruitful and as simple as possible. The underlying idea is put by Hempel (1952, 663), with reference to Carnap, as follows: ?it should be possible to develop, in terms of the reconstructed concepts, a comprehensive? and sound theoretical system?. Any criteria will be correct or incorrect only relative to these adequacy conditions (Popper, 1935, 37f; Hempel, 1952, 663).&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Surprisingly, the only substantive difference between what is included or excluded from empirical significance under Popper and Carnap&amp;rsquo;s respective criteria are as follows: Popper&amp;rsquo;s criterion functions on the level of individual sentences within a larger linguistic framework, while Carnap&amp;rsquo;s criterion functions on the level of linguistic frameworks. Since the negation of a sentence within a linguistic framework must itself be meaningful within the linguistic framework, Carnap concludes that isolated existential statements, in virtue of being negations of universal statements, must necessarily be empirically significant. Popper, on the other hand, demurs. Thus Popper&amp;nbsp;excludes isolated existential statements while Carnap&amp;rsquo;s includes isolated existential statements. If we take Carnap&amp;rsquo;s criterion to (more or less) track the intuitive concept of empirical significance as operating on the level of theoretical frameworks, Popper&amp;rsquo;s criterion satisfies the similarity condition by shifting the focus away from theoretical systems and towards sentences within a broader theoretical framework that encompasses statements that are either empirically significant or empirically non-significant; it is also as precise, fruitful, and as simple Carnap&amp;rsquo;s criterion. This bypasses the concerns raised in sections 2.2-2.3.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
In sum, if Popper&amp;rsquo;s criticism of Carnap&amp;rsquo;s treatment of isolated existential statements as empirically significant should succeed, we have suitable grounds to reject the intuitive conceptual scheme: there is a positive reason to alter or discard the intuitive conceptual scheme, since it produces an absurdity, namely, paradigmatically empirically non-significant sentences qualify as empirically significant. Kneale&amp;rsquo;s objection to this (presumably) successful criticism therefore is not like Moore&amp;rsquo;s argument: appealing to the intuition that isolated existential statements are empirically significant cannot lead to disregarding the very criticism raised by Popper (or, for that matter, any modern-day demarcationist interested in concept-revision, so long as they adhere to Carnap&amp;rsquo;s approach to concept-revision).&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
To bring this post full circle, perhaps some relevant insight can be drawn from the parable or simile of the raft&amp;ndash;one of the most famous parables in Buddhism. It is so popular that undoubtedly many people that know next to nothing about Buddhism are familiar with the simile. I do not use it in an attempt to appear somehow more knowledgeable than I am, and I do not pretend that I am providing a fair or even an accurate interpretation of the parable&amp;ndash;my familiarity with Buddhism is &lt;i&gt;rudimentary at best&lt;/i&gt;, and merely as an interested outsider, having read only a few articles on similarities between Buddhist philosophy and analytic philosophy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
However, having read the simile of the raft, I thought it does provide some solace in letting go of our intuitive concepts, even if the solace is through (intentional?) misunderstanding or (accidental?) reinterpretation for different ends; or, it may be a story we tell ourselves that helps instigate a shift in our view, not unlike moving one&amp;rsquo;s head slowly from side to side to dispel a momentary optical illusion, so that we can see the object of inquiry in a different light: nothing of real importance is lost if we let go our old picture of the world, for there was nothing there but the picture.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;tr_bq&#34; style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
The Blessed One said: &amp;ldquo;Suppose a man were traveling along a path. He would see a great expanse of water, with the near shore dubious &amp;amp; risky, the further shore secure &amp;amp; free from risk, but with neither a ferryboat nor a bridge going from this shore to the other. The thought would occur to him, &amp;lsquo;Here is this great expanse of water, with the near shore dubious &amp;amp; risky, the further shore secure &amp;amp; free from risk, but with neither a ferryboat nor a bridge going from this shore to the other. What if I were to gather grass, twigs, branches, &amp;amp; leaves and, having bound them together to make a raft, were to cross over to safety on the other shore in dependence on the raft, making an effort with my hands &amp;amp; feet?&amp;rsquo; Then the man, having gathered grass, twigs, branches, &amp;amp; leaves, having bound them together to make a raft, would cross over to safety on the other shore in dependence on the raft, making an effort with his hands &amp;amp; feet. Having crossed over to the further shore, he might think, &amp;lsquo;How useful this raft has been to me! For it was in dependence on this raft that, making an effort with my hands &amp;amp; feet, I have crossed over to safety on the further shore. Why don?t I, having hoisted it on my head or carrying on my back, go wherever I like?&amp;rsquo; What do you think, monks? Would the man, in doing that, be doing what should be done with the raft?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;tr_bq&#34; style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&amp;ldquo;No, lord.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;tr_bq&#34;&gt;
&amp;ldquo;And what should the man do in order to be doing what should be done with the raft? There is the case where the man, having crossed over, would think, &amp;lsquo;How useful this raft has been to me! For it was in dependence on this raft that, making an effort with my hands &amp;amp; feet, I have crossed over to safety on the further shore. Why don?t I, having dragged it on dry land or sinking it in the water, go wherever I like?&amp;rsquo; In doing this, he would be doing what should be done with the raft&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/mn/mn.022.than.html&#34;&gt;MN&amp;nbsp;22&lt;/a&gt;, cf. Bhikkhu, 2017, 300)&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit;&#34;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4 style=&#34;background-color: white; color: #181818; font-weight: normal; line-height: 21px; margin: 0px 0px 15px; padding: 0px;&#34;&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;font-family: inherit; font-size: large;&#34;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;background-color: white; color: #181818; font-weight: normal; line-height: 21px; margin: 0px 0px 15px; padding: 0px;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Bhikkhu,&amp;nbsp;?. (Geoffrey DeGraff) trans. (2017). &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dhammatalks.org/ebook_index.html#handfulOfLeaves&#34;&gt;Handful of Leaves: An anthology from the Sutta Pi?aka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Dennett, D.C. (1995). &lt;i&gt;Darwin&amp;rsquo;s Dangerous Idea: Evolution and the Meanings of Life.&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;New York, NY: Simon &amp;amp; Schuster.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Carnap, R. (1956). &lt;i&gt;Meaning and Necessity&lt;/i&gt;, Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2nd ed. First edition 1947.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
______. (1962). &lt;i&gt;Logical Foundations of Probability&lt;/i&gt;, Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2nd ed. First edition 1950.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
______. (1961). &lt;i&gt;Der logische Aufbau der Welt&lt;/i&gt;, 2nd ed., Hamburg: Felix Meiner, repr. 1998.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Cowherds. (2011).  &lt;i&gt;Moonshadows: Conventional Truth in Buddhist Philosophy&lt;/i&gt;. Oxford: Oxford University Press.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Finnigan, B. &amp;amp; K. Tanaka. (2011). &lt;i&gt;Carnap&amp;rsquo;s pragmatism and the two truths&lt;/i&gt;. In Moonshadows: 181-&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Nozick, R. (1980). &lt;i&gt;Anarchy, State and Utopia&lt;/i&gt;, Oxford: Blackwell. First published 1974. Basic Books.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Keynes, J.M. (1936). &lt;i&gt;The General Theory of Employment, Interest and Money. &lt;/i&gt;Palgrave Macmillan. Ch. 24 &amp;ldquo;Concluding Notes&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Kneale, W.C. (1974). The demarcation of science. &lt;i&gt;The Philosophy of Karl Popper&lt;/i&gt;, i. Vol. XIV in &lt;i&gt;The Library of Living Philosophers&lt;/i&gt;. Edited by P.A. Schilpp. La Salle, IL: Open Court: 205?217.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Popper, K.R. (&lt;sup&gt;1934&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt;). &lt;i&gt;Logik der Forschung: Zur Erkenntnistheorie der modernen Naturwissenschaft&lt;/i&gt;. Vol. 9 of &lt;i&gt;Schriften zur wissenschaftlichen Weltauffassung&lt;/i&gt;. Julius Springer: Wien.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
______. (1959). &lt;i&gt;The Logic of Scientific Discovery&lt;/i&gt;. Routledge: London and New York, NY. Translated and extended from the German original (Popper, 1935) by Karl Popper, Julius Freed, and Lan Freed. References are to Popper, K.R. (2000). &lt;i&gt;The Logic of Scientific Discovery&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
______. (1983). &lt;i&gt;Postscript to the Logic of Scientific Discovery: Realism and the Aim of Science&lt;/i&gt;, vol. iii. Routledge. Originally circulated as private galley proofs in &lt;sup&gt;1956&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;1957&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Priest, G. &amp;amp; M. Siderits, T.J.F. Tillemans. (2011). The (two) truths about truth. In &lt;i&gt;Moonshadows&lt;/i&gt;: 131-150.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Sng, Z. (2010). &lt;i&gt;The Rhetoric of Error from Locke to Kleist&lt;/i&gt;. Stanford: Stanford University Press.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Tanaka, K. (2014). In search of the semantics of emptiness. In &lt;i&gt;Nothingness in Asian Philosophy&lt;/i&gt;, JeeLou Liu and Douglas Berger (eds.), London: Routledge: 55&amp;ndash;63.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Quine, W.V.O. (1990). &lt;i&gt;Pursuit of Truth&lt;/i&gt;, Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Rowbottom, D. (2011). &lt;i&gt;Popper&amp;rsquo;s Critical Rationalism: A Philosophical Investigation&lt;/i&gt;. London: Routledge. &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An open letter to Lawrence Krauss</title>
      <link>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/post/openletter/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/post/openletter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Lawrence Krauss,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
I write to you with no expectation that you will take what I say seriously. Why take time out of your busy schedule to read the words of someone you have never heard of? And I know I am late to the party&amp;ndash;several years, in fact. I may be flogging a dead horse; however, I believe it is important to write this letter due both to your status as a &amp;lsquo;public intellectual&amp;rsquo; and your extensive history dismissing the value of philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are immensely popular, and claim that you speak from a position of authority. As you said in your article, &amp;lsquo;The Consolation of Philosophy&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;I do claim however to have some expertise in the impact of philosophy on my own field.&amp;rsquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/the-consolation-of-philos/&#34;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;) However, speaking as a &amp;lsquo;public intellectual&amp;rsquo; carries with it a responsibility: you have repeatedly denigrated philosophy in ways that would make anyone familiar with the discipline blush in embarrassment on your behalf. In this respect you have failed to uphold a core obligation as a &amp;lsquo;public intellectual&amp;rsquo;: given what you say, it&amp;rsquo;s reasonable to conclude either you&amp;rsquo;re speaking genuinely out of ignorance (and therefore lack the requisite expertise to speak about the impact of philosophy on physics), or (by your own admission) intentionally saying provocative, explosive, patently absurd things in order to get attention. Neither reflects positively on your work as a &amp;lsquo;public intellectual&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To take one relatively recent example, in a 2014 debate you held with the philosophers Dr Angie Hobbs and Mary Midgley, you said the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;I&amp;rsquo;m not suggesting philosophical questions are of no interest whatsoever. They are of interest to philosophers. And sometimes are of interest to some other people. But my point is is that they don&amp;rsquo;t really impact on progress and what&amp;rsquo;s done in the field of physics.&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Nothing that philosophers have said&amp;ndash;or are saying&amp;ndash;even philosophers of science, have any impact on how physics progresses right now. That&amp;rsquo;s not a value judgement; that&amp;rsquo;s just a fact&lt;/i&gt;.&amp;rsquo; (see: &lt;a href=&#34;https://iai.tv/video/philosophy-bites-back&#34;&gt;9:07-9:56&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extent of the falsity of your claim, which was only recently brought to my attention yesterday, requires that I write this open letter. This shall be elaborated on below, but first I must address how frequently you have said similar statements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have published this claim in writing. For example, in your article, &amp;lsquo;The Consolation of Philosophy, you say, &amp;lsquo;I, and most of the colleagues with whom I have discussed this matter, have found that philosophical speculations about physics and the nature of science are not particularly useful, and have had little or no impact upon progress in my field.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have also made this claim before, in a discussion with Daniel Dennett and Massimo Pigliucci in 2013:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;It may sound judgmental, but it&amp;rsquo;s not&amp;hellip; it is a simple empirical fact&amp;ndash;and I&amp;rsquo;m not saying it&amp;rsquo;s a good thing or a bad thing&amp;ndash;but it is a fact that the reason that most scientists don&amp;rsquo;t read philosophy is that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have any impact on what they do!&lt;/i&gt;&amp;rsquo; &amp;nbsp;(&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/9tH3AnYyAI8&#39;t=1h5m23s&#34;&gt;1:05:23-1:05:47&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pigliucci responded by saying,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;What you said a few minutes ago was both incorrect and empirically wrong. And this is what I mean by that: so if you actually take a look at the philosophy of science literature&amp;hellip; what you find are two things, or at least two things: first of all, most of philosophy of science is not at all about helping scientists answer questions, so it is no surprise that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t. So when people like your colleague, Steven Hawking, to name names, &amp;nbsp;starts off a book saying &amp;ldquo;philosophy is dead because it hasn&amp;rsquo;t contributed anything to science&amp;rdquo;, he literally does not know what he is talking about. That is not the point of philosophy of science. Right? Most of the time. So &amp;hellip; that was the conceptual part that I objected to&amp;hellip; the other part is the empirical part. It&amp;rsquo;s when you say, they don&amp;rsquo;t talk to each other, they have nothing to say to each other&amp;hellip; there are plenty of scientists that do work with philosophers &amp;nbsp;that work to clarify conceptual issues that come out of &amp;nbsp;problems in evolutionary biology. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/9tH3AnYyAI8&#39;t=1h12m35s&#34;&gt;1:12:35-1:14:48&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than retract your claim when faced with Pigliucci&amp;rsquo;s lucid response, in a recent talk with Matt Dillahunty on 5 June 2017, you &lt;i&gt;repeated&lt;/i&gt; this claim, as if Pigliucci&amp;rsquo;s criticism fell on deaf ears:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; physics has got to the point that where the real questions aren&amp;rsquo;t asked by philosophers because there&amp;rsquo;s so much down the road that the real questions require an intimate knowledge of the physics to be able to ask the right questions. And philosophers of physics (of which there are some, and I know I&amp;rsquo;ll get in trouble, of course I&amp;rsquo;ll do [inaudible]), they ask the interesting questions itself, but has no impact on the physics. Zero. &amp;lsquo;Cause most physicists can&amp;rsquo;t spell &amp;ldquo;philosophy&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip; it&amp;rsquo;s a field where they talk to each other&amp;hellip; I can tell you as a fact that there&amp;rsquo;s nothing that&amp;rsquo;s come out the philosophy of science in the last&amp;ndash;certainly since I&amp;rsquo;ve been a physicist&amp;ndash;that&amp;rsquo;s impacted on physicists. &lt;i&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s not a value judgement; that&amp;rsquo;s just a fact.&lt;/i&gt;&amp;rsquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/nSdVLXrkaNM&#39;t=1h7m53s&#34;&gt;1:07:53-1:08:50&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been lead to believe what you said was not some off-the-cuff response, but an accurate representation of what you genuinely believe. You have repeated this claim over and over again, and have not changed your mind or tempered what you said when faced with Pigliucci&amp;rsquo;s criticism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Hobbs and Midgley took you to task on a number of other claims you made in that debate in 2014, and Pigliucci explained how philosophers of biology work with biologists, I thought it would be worth addressing this particular claim in detail, not just because it is false, but because you have never been publicly held to account for the extent of how &lt;i&gt;empirically &lt;/i&gt;false that claim is in regards to physics specifically.&amp;nbsp;The falsity runs on several levels, but I will have to restrict myself to the most literal reading of what you said, and which many listeners would come away with from your talk having accepted, based on your claim of expertise: &lt;i&gt;philosophers of science have not had an impact on physics or physicists&lt;/i&gt;. That is false. You should refrain from spreading that falsehood while continuing your role as a &amp;lsquo;public intellectual&amp;rsquo;. I will now explain why you are wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;How the layperson understands what you say&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If listeners are to take what you say seriously, you are explicitly denying that philosophers of science have had any impact on current work done in physics. You are not claiming that merely &lt;i&gt;some&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;philosophers of physics have had any impact on current physics, or that the impact on current physics by philosophers of science has not been particularly important, but denying the very existence of any contribution by philosopher of science to current physics. On this point you are mistaken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In instances in which a claim is made in the form &lt;i&gt;There exists no X that is Y&lt;/i&gt;, a single counter-example is enough to refute the claim (i.e. &amp;lsquo;Here is an X that is Y&amp;rsquo;). Your claim happens to fit this very form. In brief, in order to refute your claim, I need only find a single instance of a philosopher of science having any impact on current physics by engaging in philosophical speculation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish to inform you about the work of one of the most famous philosophers of science in the twentieth century, especially outside the &amp;lsquo;ivory tower&amp;rsquo; of the academy, Sir Karl Popper.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is almost guaranteed that any class dedicated to an introduction to philosophy of science will have dedicated some time to covering Popper&amp;rsquo;s work. Any undergraduate class in the sciences that covers methodology will have mentioned him. You may have been exposed to his ideas without ever knowing it. You even mention him in your article, &amp;lsquo;The Consolation of Philosophy&amp;rsquo;, (although only disparagingly), and have mentioned elsewhere that you have read Popper (more on this later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If anyone were to speak about philosophy of science as you did, and yet failed to recognise how the output of one of the most famous philosophers of science of the twentieth century undermined your claim, it calls into question their awareness of some of the most elementary issues in history of science in the twentieth century. Let me more explicit: either (1)&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;you do not understand the extent of your mistake, because you do not know what you are talking about or &lt;/i&gt;(2) &lt;i&gt;(by your own admission) you intentionally say falsehoods in order to get attention&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In what follows, I&amp;rsquo;d like to elaborate on Popper&amp;rsquo;s work on the foundations of Quantum Mechanics (QM), specifically his work on developing a number of &lt;i&gt;Gedankenexperiments&lt;/i&gt;&amp;ndash;philosophical speculations that have influenced physics to this day. This involves delving into history of twentieth century physics, so I hope you do not mind a brief overview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I briefly cover six examples of how Popper influenced physics and physicists: (1) Popper&amp;rsquo;s Experiment (PE) as first developed in 1934, (2) Popper&amp;rsquo;s criticism of Birkoff and von Neumann in his 1968 paper, (3) the 1980 Vigier, Garuccio and Popper Experiment (VGP), (4 &amp;amp; 5) Popper&amp;rsquo;s papers on EPR (1985) and Bell&amp;rsquo;s inequalities (1988), and (6) Popper&amp;rsquo;s revised experiment (EPR-like) published in 1980.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
Example 1: Popper&#39;s Experiment&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1934, Popper published a scientific paper setting out a &lt;i&gt;Gedankenexperiment&lt;/i&gt; designed to undermine the Copenhagen Interpretation of Quantum Mechanics (CIQM), specifically Heisenberg&amp;rsquo;s interpretation of uncertainty (1934a). This experiment is often referred to in the literature as &lt;i&gt;Popper&amp;rsquo;s Experiment &lt;/i&gt;(hereafter &amp;lsquo;PE&amp;rsquo;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That same year, Popper published his book,&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Logik der Forshung &lt;/i&gt;(1934b). He devoted Chapter IX of his book to foundations of QM, criticising a number of assumptions made in CIQM, elaborating on PE and setting out an early statistical interpretation of QM. Unfortunately for Popper, Einstein wrote a letter to Popper in 1935 detailing fundamental problems with the &lt;i&gt;Gedankenexperiment&lt;/i&gt;;&amp;nbsp;Bohr met with Popper at a conference in 1936 to address similar flaws in the experimental setup of PE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this relevant? After an analysis of this historical episode, Redhead (1995) concluded, &amp;lsquo;one can even speculate that Einstein was influenced by Popper&amp;rsquo; in deriving the EPR experiment in 1935. If true, Popper&amp;rsquo;s development of PE in 1934 would be sufficient to refute your claim. EPR is, I hope you would be willing to acknowledge, of some interest in physics even today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may insist that (&lt;i&gt;contra&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;Redhead)&amp;nbsp;Popper&amp;rsquo;s 1934 version of his&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Gedankenexperiment&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;would not qualify as having &amp;lsquo;any impact on on how physics progresses &lt;i&gt;right now&lt;/i&gt;.&amp;rsquo; (emphasis added) It&amp;rsquo;s a historical curiosity at best, relegated to a footnote in history of twentieth century physics. That&amp;rsquo;s a reasonable position to hold, of course, but I would like to hear from you &lt;i&gt;why&lt;/i&gt; you would reject PE as influencing physics. It is an obvious example, almost trivial. How do you account for PE? What do you think a layperson will believe having heard what you said on numerous occasions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
Example 2: Popper&#39;s 1968 paper&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faced with the failure of PE, Popper expressed shame at his relative lack of expertise in physics, and turned his attention to problems in scientific methodology and political philosophy. However, by the late-1940s, and after speaking with the physicist Arthur March, Popper focused again on foundations of QM in his English translation to&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Logik&lt;/i&gt;, including Appendix xi in &lt;i&gt;The Logic of Scientific Discovery&lt;/i&gt;. By the mid-1950s this work had developed into &amp;lsquo;The Postscript&amp;rsquo;, a three-volume continuation of work done in &lt;i&gt;Logik&lt;/i&gt;, which would be periodically worked on for thirty years, finally published in the early 1980s. (We&amp;rsquo;ll return to &amp;lsquo;The Postscript&amp;rsquo; in Example 6.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the time spent working on the &amp;lsquo;Postscript&amp;rsquo;, Popper published a 1968 paper, &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v219/n5155/abs/219682a0.html?foxtrotcallback=true&#34;&gt;Birkoff and von Neumann&amp;rsquo;s Interpretation of Quantum Mechanics&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;. In the paper, Popper claimed to have found an error in a famous paper by Birkhoff and von Neumann, &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/1968621&#39;seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents&#34;&gt;The Logic of Quantum Mechanics&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; (1936). This foray into QM was far better received by De Brogile, van der Waerden and Bunge, amongst other physicists. If this 1968 paper had any impact on current physics, no matter how small, this would be sufficient to refute your claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to hear from you why you don&amp;rsquo;t accept Popper&amp;rsquo;s 1968 paper as having any influence on physics or physicists. You may also attempt to dismiss Popper&amp;rsquo;s 1968 paper as being of little interest for current work in foundations of QM, or perhaps little more than correcting a minor error in a paper published in the 1930s, certainly not something on the forefront of &lt;i&gt;current&lt;/i&gt; work in physics. But you&amp;rsquo;d first have to be aware of the 1968 paper and &lt;i&gt;argue for&lt;/i&gt; its irrelevance, rather than make sweeping claims about every single philosopher of science, dismissing a whole field without ever actually &lt;i&gt;arguing&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;for that position. Will the layperson leave your talks or having read your opinion pieces having learned something new, interesting and valuable, or will they leave believing falsehoods? The question answers itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
Example 3: The 1980 Vigier, Garuccio &amp;amp; Popper experiment&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Shields (2012, 4) notes, &amp;lsquo;Popper&amp;rsquo;s solitary efforts to offer a different view of quantum phenomena acquire a different status in the early 1980&amp;rsquo;s. By this time, he had acquired colleagues in the theoretical physics community, one of whom, French physicist Jean-Pierre Vigier, had an international reputation.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 1980, Viger and Augusto Garuccio had worked on a modification of the Mandel-Pfleegor experiment (Garuccio and Vigier, 1980). Viger had been in communication with Popper for some time about developing this experiment, and in private correspondence between Viger and Popper dated 15 September, 1980, Viger wrote to Popper, saying, &amp;lsquo;&amp;hellip; your proposal to improve on our laser experiment is excellent. In fact I am thinking of including it into a more detailed discussion [&amp;hellip;]. Would you do us the pleasure of co-signing this improved version with Garuccio and myself?&amp;rsquo; (PA, 358 / 25) Popper refused this invitation for co-authorship, claiming he did &amp;lsquo;not deserve it&amp;rsquo; (PA, 358 / 25), but Vigier insisted, saying, &amp;lsquo;I feel your suggestion [&amp;hellip;] is so important that I would not dare publish it without your signature&amp;rsquo; (PA, 487 / 11). Popper gave in, and two publications were printed in &lt;i&gt;Epistemological Letters &lt;/i&gt;(1981a) and &lt;i&gt;Physics Letters A &lt;/i&gt;(1981b) detailing the Vigier, Garuccio and Popper (VGP) experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may believe that (&lt;i&gt;contra&lt;/i&gt; Vigier) Popper&amp;rsquo;s contributions to VGP were nominal at best. Perhaps you dismiss Popper&amp;rsquo;s contribution here, too. That is certainly possible. The two papers co-authored with Viger and Garuccio could have been nothing more than a name on a paper added due to Viger feeling indebted to Popper. If so, I would appreciate hearing from you why you do not believe these papers had any influence on physics or physicists, because since you claim to speak as an authority on the subject, you don&amp;rsquo;t appear to be aware of VGP in the slightest. The layperson listening to your talk or reading your opinion pieces will surely leave thinking that Popper never contributed to VGP&amp;ndash;after all, they&amp;rsquo;ll leave thinking that philosophers do not contribute to physics, full stop.
&lt;h4&gt;
Examples 4 and 5: Popper&amp;rsquo;s papers on EPR and Bell&amp;rsquo;s theorem&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may also have good reason to dismiss Popper&amp;rsquo;s papers, &amp;lsquo;Towards a Local Explanatory Theory of the Einstein-Podolsky-Rosen-Bohm experiment&amp;rsquo; (Popper &amp;amp; Angelidis, 1985) and &amp;lsquo;Bell&amp;rsquo;s theorem: a note on locality&amp;rsquo; (Van der Merwe, 1988, 413-417). You may respond that these papers were (rightly or wrongly) neglected, so even if they could have influenced physics or physicists, they did not. You could, but that would require engaging with the evidence that &lt;i&gt;prima facie&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;undermines your claim&amp;ndash;the evidence that you don&amp;rsquo;t appear to be aware of&amp;ndash;the evidence that, had it been available, would have presumably temperedx your grand statements about an entire field, and injected some needed nuance or clarification that would help the layperson, which is sorely lacking from most of your public statements on this matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
Example 6: The &#39;EPR-like&#39; experiment&amp;nbsp;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popper revisited his original &lt;i&gt;Gedankenexperiment &lt;/i&gt;in a letter to Vigier (1980, PA, &lt;sup&gt;358&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;25&lt;/sub&gt;), in light of the EPR experiment, to develop an &lt;i&gt;experimentum crucis&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;(hereafter referred to as &amp;lsquo;EPR-like&amp;rsquo;) that bore no relation to the GVP experiment. In 1982 &amp;lsquo;The Postscript&amp;rsquo; was finally published. The third volume, &lt;i&gt;Quantum Theory and Schism in Physics&lt;/i&gt;, included the EPR-like experiment in the Preface, &amp;lsquo;On a Realistic and Commonsense Interpretation of Quantum Theory&amp;rsquo; (Popper 1982a). While the volume may not have been read by physicists, he then published a three-page physics paper in a collected volume for Carl Friedrich von&amp;nbsp;Weizscker on the EPR-like experiment (1982b). However, the EPR-like experiment languished. By 1985, Popper said, &amp;lsquo;I plead here only that my experiment [EPR-like] should be conducted by somebody&amp;rsquo; (1985, 10).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this time, several physicists and mathematicians responded negatively to Popper&amp;rsquo;s forays into physics. Henry Krips (1984, 254-261) disagreed with Popper on the outcome of the experiment; in 1985, Anthony Sudbery published a paper titled &amp;lsquo;Popper&amp;rsquo;s variant of the EPR experiment does not test the Copenhagen interpretation&amp;rsquo; &amp;nbsp;(Sudbery, 1985), and expanded on his critique at a conference later that year; the physicists Matthew J. Collett and Rodney Loudon published a letter in &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;in 1987 claiming &amp;lsquo;the [EPR-like] experiment cannot provide a crucial test of quantum mechanical intepretations&amp;rsquo; (Collett and Loudon, 1987). However, as Qureshi (2012, 2) noted, &amp;lsquo;none of the objections raised against Popper&amp;rsquo;s experiment could convincingly demonstrate if there was a problem with the proposal.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the late 1980s there were developments in physics that simplified the production of entangled photons, leading to work done in quantum optics. In 1999, Yanhua Shih and Yoon-Ho Kim carried out the first test of EPR-like, and discovered an agreement with Popper&amp;rsquo;s predictions. The paper, &lt;i&gt;Experimental Realization of Popper&amp;rsquo;s Experiment: Violation of the Uncertainty Principle? &lt;/i&gt;(2000) was published in &lt;i&gt;Foundations of Physics&lt;/i&gt;. This lead to more than a dozen papers over the next three years on EPR-like (e.g. Hunter 2003, Short 2001).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, papers continue to be published on EPR-like &lt;i&gt;to this day&lt;/i&gt;. Just search &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?q=%22Popper%27s+Experiment%22&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;as_sdt=0%2C5&amp;amp;as_ylo=1999&amp;amp;as_yhi=2017&#34;&gt;Popper&amp;rsquo;s Experiment&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; on scholar.google.com and see for yourself. There&amp;rsquo;s been more than seventy-five articles published since 1999 that reference EPR-like. Thirty-five years after its publication in 1982, and eighteen years after it was realised by Shih and Kim, there continues to be a debate in the physics community over EPR-like. If there could be any counter-examples to your claim, EPR-like is it. The matter is closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
Am I just being pedantic? No.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may wonder why I have spent so much time responding to your claim. The reasons are many: you have made this claim several times, most recently in June of this year; you frequently make these sorts of comments disparaging philosophy of science, with no regard to history of science; this claim is but one of many sweeping claims you have made that are simply &lt;i&gt;false&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;on basic matters of fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of a general pattern to your public statements: you routinely overgeneralise. You constantly engage in hyperbole. You repeatedly exaggerate. You make radical and inflammatory claims without supporting them with evidence. You assert things that are &lt;i&gt;demonstrably false&lt;/i&gt;. I will now cover several examples of you committing these acts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an interview with Ross Anderson in 2012, you said,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; physics has encroached on philosophy. Philosophy used to be a field that had content, but then &amp;ldquo;natural philosophy&amp;rdquo; became physics, and physics has only continued to make inroads. Every time there&amp;rsquo;s a leap in physics, it encroaches on these areas that philosophers have carefully sequestered away to themselves, and so then you have this natural resentment on the part of philosophers. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2012/04/has-physics-made-philosophy-and-religion-obsolete/256203/&#34;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would take a few thousand words and far more of my time than I&amp;rsquo;d like to address, but due to your status as a &amp;lsquo;public intellectual&amp;rsquo;, few people press you to provide an iota of evidence for this claim. &lt;i&gt;On what grounds&lt;/i&gt; do you believe physics and philosophy address the same problems? &lt;i&gt;What evidence&lt;/i&gt; supports your claim that philosophers resent physicists? Is it &lt;i&gt;every time&lt;/i&gt;, or is it only sometimes? What supports your claim that philosophers &amp;lsquo;have carefully sequestered&amp;rsquo; areas away from physics? And how do you account for all the readily available evidence that refutes your claims?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that same interview with Andersen, you said,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philosophy is a field that, unfortunately, reminds me of that old Woody Allen joke, &amp;lsquo;those that can&amp;rsquo;t do, teach, and those that can&amp;rsquo;t teach, teach gym.&amp;rsquo; And the worst part of philosophy is the philosophy of science; the only people, as far as I can tell, that read work by philosophers of science are other philosophers of science. It has no impact on physics what so ever. &amp;hellip; they have every right to feel threatened, because science progresses and philosophy doesn&amp;rsquo;t. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2012/04/has-physics-made-philosophy-and-religion-obsolete/256203/&#34;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is there to say? What &lt;i&gt;evidence &lt;/i&gt;supports your claim that philosophy does not progress? Did you conduct any studies on the psychology of philosophers of science? Are philosophers of science genuinely threatened, or is that just hyperbole and exaggeration designed to be provocative?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a 2012 interview with Julian Baggini, you claim,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;To first approximation all the answerable ones [questions] end up moving into the domain of empirical knowledge, aka science.&amp;rsquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/science/2012/sep/09/science-philosophy-debate-julian-baggini-lawrence-krauss&#34;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Really&lt;/i&gt;? What evidence supports your claims? How do you account for the obvious and well-known counter-examples?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One line in your 2012 interview with Andersen speaks volumes about your abdication of your responsibility to the public to speak truthfully: &amp;lsquo;&lt;i&gt;Well, yeah, I mean, look I was being provocative, as I tend to do every now and then in order to get people&amp;rsquo;s attention&lt;/i&gt;.&amp;rsquo; It has been five years now since that interview, and you are still trying to be provocative, trying to get attention. But you gain attention by&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;speaking demonstrable falsehoods &lt;/i&gt;while&amp;nbsp;speaking from a position of (supposed) authority.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this day you still repeat this old canard. Recently, you said,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;But does it [physics] need philosophers? That is the question. The answer is not so much any more. It did early on. &amp;nbsp;&amp;hellip; Physics &amp;hellip; has grown out of it. Now there is very little relationship between physicists do and what even philosophers of science do. &amp;hellip; These questions that they raise are vitally interesting in many areas of human activity. It is just in physics they are not.&amp;rsquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reasonablefaith.org/the-latest-from-lawrence-krauss-and-neil-deGrasse-tyson&#34;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other related claims you have made&amp;ndash;all of them said without providing any evidence or argumentation to support them. Take, for example, a number of absurd claims you made just in a panel with philosophers and theologians in Stockholm in 2013, as an illustration at how frequently you say things that are&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;wrong&lt;/i&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Science demonstrates&amp;ndash;and it&amp;rsquo;s the only area of human activity in my opinion that demonstrates that people can work together.&amp;rsquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/LjkkJYQnZtY&#39;t=17m7s&#34;&gt;17:07-17:15&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;And so it&amp;rsquo;s well-motivated for reasons completely different than explaining the origin of our universe and providing a context to answer this ridiculous question that the philosophers asked. &amp;hellip; The question of interest for philosophers is precisely the question that has absolutely no interest. &amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;m really thrilled that the philosophers are interested in it, because they can go on asking their questions and we&amp;rsquo;ll go on making progress.&amp;rsquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/LjkkJYQnZtY&#39;t=22m38s&#34;&gt;22:38-23:15&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;That may not be the question of interest to philosophers, but I point out that &lt;i&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t give a damn&lt;/i&gt;.&amp;rsquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/LjkkJYQnZtY&#39;t=25m24s&#34;&gt;25:25-25:35&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Can we test these ideas, and if we can&amp;rsquo;t, then we call it impotent.&amp;rsquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/LjkkJYQnZtY&#39;t=28m17s&#34;&gt;28:17-28:22&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;If we can&amp;rsquo;t [make predictions]&amp;hellip; then it&amp;rsquo;s complete mental masturbation.&amp;rsquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/LjkkJYQnZtY&#39;t=28m28s&#34;&gt;28:28-28:34&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;The only knowledge that matters is the knowledge that comes to us from the universe.&amp;rsquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/LjkkJYQnZtY&#39;t=32m46s&#34;&gt;32:46-32:50&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;I do dismiss certain aspects of philosophy. &amp;hellip; You&amp;rsquo;re absolutely right: a lot of what I&amp;rsquo;m doing is philosophy if you call philosophy &amp;ldquo;critical thinking and analysis&amp;rdquo; &amp;hellip; [but] the philosophy doesn&amp;rsquo;t add to the science&amp;rsquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/LjkkJYQnZtY&#39;t=35m47s&#34;&gt;35:47-36:08&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;If you can&amp;rsquo;t empirically measure it, it isn&amp;rsquo;t knowledge.&amp;rsquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/LjkkJYQnZtY&#39;t=41m43s&#34;&gt;41:43-41:47&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;I&amp;rsquo;m an empiricist, so my empirical proof that philosophy is irrelevant is that no scientist knows anything about philosophy, but look what&amp;rsquo;s happened! In spite of the fact that we don&amp;rsquo;t know anything about philosophy&amp;ndash;or at least we don&amp;rsquo;t read philosophy&amp;ndash;we&amp;rsquo;ve been able to discover all these things about the universe&amp;hellip;&amp;rsquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/LjkkJYQnZtY&#39;t=42m48s&#34;&gt;42:48-43:05&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;The only philosophy I need to do is not the philosophy I learned from Kuhn or Popper or any&amp;ndash;although I read them all&amp;ndash;I learned the philosophy of science from Feynman.&amp;rsquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/LjkkJYQnZtY&#39;t=51m29s&#34;&gt;51:28-51:40&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These quotes were from one relatively recent dialogue with philosophers. Every single one of those things you said is a cavalier, irresponsible way for a &amp;lsquo;public intellectual&amp;rsquo; to act. Every single one of these things you said would require replies running into the thousands of words. Whole books have been written on these subjects by eminent experts covering why&amp;ndash;in excruciating detail&amp;ndash;what you said is false. What you said is so fundamentally wrong that it is difficult to figure out where to begin. Some of what you said is so absurd that it leads me to question whether you are telling the truth, have forgotten everything you claim to have read, or cannot handle complex, nuanced positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take, for example, (10): your claim that you read Popper and Kuhn, but you learned philosophy of science from Richard Feynman. If the only philosophy of science you learned was from Feynman, then how can you account for the fact that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0KmimDq4cSU&#34;&gt;Feynman&amp;rsquo;s public statements on philosophy of science&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;are &lt;i&gt;nothing but a warmed over, secondhand, inchoate, childish, naive version of Popper&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/i&gt;? Anyone that has read Feynman and Popper can see this. You, however, have not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, how can you help to deal with the fact that there exists &lt;i&gt;far&lt;/i&gt; more to philosophy of science than a bastardisation of a relatively unpopular position in philosophy of science? What you said in every one of those cases is, like (10), no better than the creationist asking the scientist, &amp;lsquo;If humans evolved from monkeys, then why are there still monkeys?&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a layperson were to take what you say seriously, they will conclude that philosophers haven&amp;rsquo;t contributed to physics in hundreds of years, philosophers don&amp;rsquo;t contribute much of anything at all, physics doesn&amp;rsquo;t need philosophy, and philosophy is useless and impotent. Thus, they will be worse off reading or listening to you if they wanted to learn about the relationship between philosophy and science than had they never heard of your name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, when you say, &amp;lsquo;Nothing that philosophers have said&amp;ndash;or are saying&amp;ndash;even philosophers of science, have any impact on how physics progresses right now&amp;rsquo;, I take you to mean what you said, for you have said it again and again, refusing to listen to criticism. And on this point, you are demonstrably&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;wrong&lt;/i&gt;, you have been told exactly why you are wrong several times now, and yet you don&amp;rsquo;t stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Correcting your mistakes often takes up far more time and space than you&amp;rsquo;d imagine, and by the time someone has sat down and done the real work of showing why you are mistaken, you&amp;rsquo;ll have moved on to make &lt;i&gt;another&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;sweeping claim disparaging philosophy that is simply &lt;i&gt;false&lt;/i&gt;. It is simply easy to &amp;lsquo;shoot from the hip&amp;rsquo; like you do, speaking about whole disciplines. It is a never-ending game of following behind you, trying to rectify your errors, while the public continues to be misinformed by the nonsense you spout. Here is one more example that illustrates how you make &lt;i&gt;so many&lt;/i&gt; elementary mistakes that someone that wasn&amp;rsquo;t considered a &amp;lsquo;public intellectual&amp;rsquo; would be far more cautious before sticking their foot in their mouth. At one point earlier in the 2014 debate with Hobbs and Midgley, you say,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m always amazed when people bring up Aristotle as a source of knowledge and wisdom: he was the one, by the way, who thought objects fell proportional &amp;nbsp;to their weight and thought women had a different number of teeth than men because he never bothered to look. And so, um, uh, this kind of &amp;ldquo;ancient wisdom&amp;rdquo; that is [inaudible] amusing to me, because that&amp;rsquo;s what science has done, has taken us away from an ancient lack of wisdom and forced us to&amp;ndash;forced our beliefs to conform to the evidence of reality. (&lt;a href=&#34;https://iai.tv/video/philosophy-bites-back&#34;&gt;6:44-7:12&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robin Herbert addressed both these very points in a post on &lt;i&gt;Scientia Salon&lt;/i&gt;, &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://scientiasalon.wordpress.com/2014/10/03/rescuing-aristotle/&#34;&gt;Rescuing Aristotle&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;, detailing how many people uncritically accept without any examination of the evidence that Aristotle failed to conduct observations of falling objects or count teeth. And yet he did not: Aristotle&amp;rsquo;s observations in physics and biology were&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;faulty&lt;/i&gt;; Aristotle &lt;i&gt;was&lt;/i&gt; making observations, &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; making declarations from the armchair! If you enjoy physics, I suggest you read the article, &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1312.4057&#34;&gt;Aristotle&amp;rsquo;s Physics: a Physicist&amp;rsquo;s Look&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; and see for yourself. This information is readily available. And yet, like your repeated insistence that Aristotle&amp;rsquo;s physical and biological theories were developed entirely conceptually, and without empirical import, given your pronouncements on philosophy this past decade, your comments reveal that you fail to confirm your beliefs to the evidence. If anyone here is engaged in armchair musings and idle speculation, it is you, Lawrence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned previously, you find it permissible to speak broadly about the psychology of philosophers as a whole, that they feel &amp;lsquo;threatened&amp;rsquo; by scientists and are &amp;lsquo;resentful&amp;rsquo; of science. Two can play at this game of uncharitable psychoanalysis. At this point in your career as a &amp;lsquo;public intellectual&amp;rsquo;, and given the evidence presented so far, I cannot tell whether you say these things from a position of genuine, deeply-entrenched, blithe ignorance or ineptitude or you are a provocateur that spreads disinformation to the public in order to remain relevant. &lt;i&gt;So which is it?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
Being as charitable as possible&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I covered the contributions of&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;one single philosopher of science&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;to the theoretical foundations of physics in developing a number of&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Gedankenexperiments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;It takes time and energy to write an open letter such as this, all because your continue to choose to speak so broadly, so sweepingly, so loosely, so disparagingly of philosophy&amp;ndash;all without providing a lick of evidence to back up your claims. Setting out the evidence takes time and energy. You should know that. And now that the evidence is available, and if you should ever read this letter, you now know the examples I provided shut down your absurd talking-point. Retire it immediately. Publicly recant. Stop saying these things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But hold off for one moment. Let&amp;rsquo;s assume that I&amp;rsquo;m engaging in histrionics or being pedantic. I may be making a mountain range out of all these molehills. I may be misreading what you said. Perhaps you merely misspoke on numerous occasions, or engaged in hyperbole, or exaggerated for effect and to get attention (after all, you do this fairly often, and said you say these things to get attention) and what you &lt;i&gt;really&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;meant to say that philosophers of science&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;when doing philosophy of science&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;have never&amp;nbsp;made an impact on how physics progresses right now. Who knows? After all, unlike your previous comments directed towards philosophy and philosophers (we&amp;rsquo;re &amp;lsquo;threatened&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;resentful&amp;rsquo;), we ought to uphold the principle of charity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s put aside all the issues surrounding how &lt;i&gt;irresponsible &lt;/i&gt;it is for a &amp;lsquo;public intellectual&amp;rsquo; to speak in a way that a layperson will have reasonable grounds to interpret you as saying that philosophers of science have &lt;i&gt;never&lt;/i&gt; contributed to current work in physics. What could be your best defence? You wrote elsewhere, &amp;lsquo;There have been people who one can classify as philosophers who have contributed usefully to this discussion [of quantum mechanics], but when they have, they have been essentially doing physics, and have published in physics journals&amp;rsquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/science/2012/sep/09/science-philosophy-debate-julian-baggini-lawrence-krauss&#34;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;). Perhaps that&amp;rsquo;s all you meant to say: since the only answerable questions are scientific questions, philosophy is only useful&lt;i&gt; when it is physics in disguise&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, even if we&amp;rsquo;re being as charitable as possible to what you said, your talking point is then obviously inchoate, since out of one side of your mouth you claim philosophers &lt;i&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/i&gt; contribute to physics, while out of the other side you say they &lt;i&gt;have&lt;/i&gt; contributed. It&amp;rsquo;s a wonderful &amp;lsquo;tails I win; heads you lose&amp;rsquo; case, isn&amp;rsquo;t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If so, and you&amp;rsquo;re really just saying something clearly incoherent, I&amp;rsquo;m afraid that my letter would have to be far longer than it presently is, because, as you can see, your habit of speaking so authoritatively in that one sentence required writing several thousand words to clarify your mistake (or exaggeration, or hyperbole intentionally designed to get attention) so that the layperson did not leave having listened or read what you wrote with the mistaken belief that philosophers of science do not contribute to physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the time spent to clarify error and explicate how mistaken the error was tracked the degree of error, and you meant &lt;i&gt;only&lt;/i&gt; that philosophy of science &lt;i&gt;qua &lt;/i&gt;philosophy of science does not contribute to physics, I&amp;rsquo;m afraid that my letter would run far longer, for your mistake would not be simply a matter of fact (here is the counter-example, we can all move on), but of your entire &lt;i&gt;worldview&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have the fundamentally mistaken belief that, as you said, &amp;lsquo;If you can&amp;rsquo;t empirically measure it, it isn&amp;rsquo;t knowledge.&amp;rsquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/LjkkJYQnZtY&#39;t=41m43s&#34;&gt;41:43-41:47&lt;/a&gt;). This is not just scientism, but the sort of scientism usually relegated to online bodybuilding forums. No respectable &amp;lsquo;public intellectual&amp;rsquo; ought to say such rubbish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if you are genuinely ignorant, any examination of the literature would reveal that philosophers of science continue to contribute to physics, &lt;i&gt;even if it isn&amp;rsquo;t the primary aim of philosophy of science&lt;/i&gt;. Pigliucci has already told you this, and yet you continue to spread this bilge. Any &lt;i&gt;Gedankenexperiments&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;developed by philosophers of science is an &lt;i&gt;added benefit&lt;/i&gt; of what philosophers of physics do. Some philosophers of science, like Karl Popper, &lt;i&gt;have manifestly contributed to physics&lt;/i&gt;. End of story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, if we limit our understanding of &amp;lsquo;contributions to physics&amp;rsquo; to work more orientated towards philosophy of science as it is usually construed, separate from philosophy of physics, any examination of what philosophers of science&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;do&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;would reveal that philosophers of science do significant work &lt;i&gt;that is of considerable interest to&amp;nbsp;physicists.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know what philosophers of science write is of considerable interest to physicists because these debates in philosophy of science are directed at addressing core problems in physics, methodology and statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know what philosophers of science write is of interest to physicists because there are innumerable examples of physicists engaging with philosophers of science about these issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the most praised scientists in the past century have produced work in philosophy of science, and explicitly claim a debt to work done in philosophy of science. Albert Einstein even has a volume published in The Library of Living Philosophers series, Vol. XII: &lt;i&gt;Albert Einstein: Philosopher-Scientist&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;(1949). The evidence is all around you, if only you&amp;rsquo;d listen.&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;You&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;may not be interested in these questions. Well then bully for you! That says far more about your disinterest in these questions than it does about physics and physicists that exist beyond your parochial views. The rest of the physics community will continue to engage with philosophy of science. The existence of the &lt;i&gt;physics community&lt;/i&gt; refutes your claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Summing up&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike you, I&amp;rsquo;m not a &amp;lsquo;public intellectual&amp;rsquo;. I lack the cultural cachet that you do, and I have to provide&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;evidence&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;and&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;arguments&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;for my claims, rather than, as you do, say Aristotle thought objects fell proportional to their weight and women have different number of teeth than men &amp;lsquo;because he never bothered to look&amp;rsquo;. No, Lawrence, given your record, I&amp;rsquo;m beginning to believe&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;you never bothered to look&lt;/i&gt;. You routinely form opinions without ever taking the time to examine the evidence. You infer, based on your personal experience, that you don&amp;rsquo;t rely on anything from philosophers of science (just scientists like Feynman, parroting back positions in philosophy of science set forward by Popper like a bad game of Chinese Whispers), and conclude that physicists as a group don&amp;rsquo;t take anything of value from philosophy of science. &lt;i&gt;Bull&lt;/i&gt;. Open your eyes, your ears, your mind, and listen for once to your critics.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All is not lost. If the past decade&amp;rsquo;s-worth of misinformation you promulgate is due solely to your ignorance of philosophy, &lt;i&gt;you can still change&lt;/i&gt;. Stop relying on your armchair reasoning from your misconceptions about what &lt;i&gt;&amp;nbsp;you think&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;philosophy of science is, stand up,&amp;nbsp;and do the legwork. It may be difficult at first, but there are dozens of philosophers that are willing to help you. You say you care about the evidence, so go, dissuade yourself from your false beliefs. If you wish for guidance, I can get you in touch with philosophers of science, philosophers of physics, historians of science, historians of philosophy of science, &lt;i&gt;and physicists&lt;/i&gt;. They can&amp;nbsp;help you learn and grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If, however, you are saying these things because you want attention, you do a disservice to your audience, not just for incorrectly dismissing philosophy and perpetuating a naive, base form of scientism, but for saying things that are &lt;i&gt;patently not true&lt;/i&gt;, and with no respect to the truth. If so, &lt;i&gt;you just don&amp;rsquo;t care&lt;/i&gt; what you say to the public, so long as you remain a &amp;lsquo;public intellectual&amp;rsquo;. If you don&amp;rsquo;t want to change, if you don&amp;rsquo;t care about how your words affect others, then you simply &amp;lsquo;don&amp;rsquo;t give a damn&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Kind Regards,&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Nathan Oseroff&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
Bibliography&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Collett, Matthew J. and Rodney Loudon. 1987. Analysis of a Proposed Crucial Test of Quantum
Mechanics. &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt; 326, 671.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Garuccio, Augusto, Karl R. Popper &amp;amp; Jean-Pierre Vigier. 1981a. An Experiment to Interpret E.P.R. Action at a
Distance: The Possible Detection of Real de Broglie Waves. &lt;i&gt;Epist. Lett&lt;/i&gt;. 30: 21.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Garuccio, Augusto, Karl R. Popper &amp;amp; Jean-Pierre Vigier. 1981b. Possible Direct Physical Detection of de Broglie
Waves. &lt;i&gt;Physics Letters A&lt;/i&gt; 86(8): 397-400.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Garuccio, Augusto &amp;amp; Jean-Pierre Vigier. 1980. Possible Experimental Test of the Causal Stochastic Interpretation of
Quantum Mechanics: Physical reality of de Broglie waves.&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Foundations of Physics&lt;/i&gt;, 10(9-10): 797-801.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Hunter, Geoffrey, &amp;nbsp;2003. Realism in the Realized Popper&amp;rsquo;s Experiment, &lt;i&gt;American Institute of
Physics Conference Proceedings&lt;/i&gt; 646, 243-248.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Kim, Y., and Y. Shih. 1999. Experimental Realisation of Popper&amp;rsquo;s Experiment: Violation of the Uncertainty
Principle?. &lt;i&gt;Foundations of Physics&lt;/i&gt; 29,12.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Krips, Henry. 1984. Popper, Propensities and Quantum Theory. &lt;i&gt;The British Journal for the Philosophy of Science&lt;/i&gt;
35(3), 253-274.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
PA, Popper Archive, Box/Folder: 358 / 25. AAU, Klagenfurt (Austria)/Hoover Institution, Stanford (California).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
PA, Popper Archive, Box/Folder: 487 / 11. AAU, Klagenfurt (Austria)/Hoover Institution, Stanford (California)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Popper, Karl R. 1934. Zur Kritik der Undenauigkeitsrelationen. &lt;i&gt;Die Naturwissenschaften &lt;/i&gt;22: 807-808.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
_______. 1968. Birkhoff and von Neumann&amp;rsquo;s Interpretation of Quantum Mechanics. &lt;i&gt;Nature&lt;/i&gt; 219: 682-685.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
_______. 1982a. &lt;i&gt;Quantum Theory and the Schism in Physics. Vol. III of the Postscript to the Logic of Scientific
Discovery&lt;/i&gt;, W. W. Bartley III (ed.). London: Hutchinson; Totowa: Rowman and Littlefield.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
_______. 1982b. Proposal for a Simplified New Variant of the Experiment of Einstein, Podolsky and Rosen. In
Klaus Michael Meyer (ed.). Physik, Philisophie und Politik (Festschrift for C. F. von Weizscker&amp;rsquo;s 70th
birthday). Munich: Carl Hanser Verlag: 310?313.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
_______. 1985. Realism in Quantum Mechanics and a New Version of the EPR Experiment. In Gino Tarozzi
and Alwyn van der Merwe (eds.). &lt;i&gt;Open Questions in Quantum Physics&lt;/i&gt;. Dordrecht: Reidel Publishing Co.: 3-25.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Popper, Karl R. and Thomas D. Angelidis. 1985. Towards a Local Explanatory Theory of the Einstein-PodolskyRosen-Bohm
Experiment. In Pekka Lahti and Peter Mittelstaedt (eds.). Symposium on the Foundations of
Modern Physics. World Scientific Publishing Co.: 37-49.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Qureshi, Tabish. 2012. Popper&amp;rsquo;s Experiment: A Modern Perspective. &lt;i&gt;Quanta&lt;/i&gt; 1: 19-32.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Redhead, Michael. 1995. Popper and the Quantum Theory. In Anthony O&amp;rsquo;Hear (ed.). &lt;i&gt;Karl Popper: Philosophy and
Problems&lt;/i&gt;. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press: 163-176.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Shields, William M. 2012. A Historical Survey of Sir Karl Popper&amp;rsquo;s Contribution to Quantum Mechanics.
&lt;i&gt;Quanta&lt;/i&gt; 1(1): 1-12.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Shih, Yanhua, Kim, Yoon-Ho, 2000. Experimental Realization of Popper&amp;rsquo;s Experiment?
Violation of the Uncertainty Principle? &lt;i&gt;Fortschr. Phys.&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;48: 463-471.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
________. 2000b. Quantum Entanglement: from Popper&amp;rsquo;s Experiment to Quantum Eraser, &lt;i&gt;Frontiers of Laser Physics and Quantum Optics&lt;/i&gt;, 71-90.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Short, A.J. 2001. Popper&amp;rsquo;s Experiment and Conditional Uncertainty Relations, &lt;i&gt;Foundations
of Physics Letters &lt;/i&gt;14(3): 275-284.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Sudbery, Anthony. 1985. Popper&amp;rsquo;s Variant of the EPR Experiment Does not Test the Copenhagen Interpretation.
&lt;i&gt;Philosophy of Science&lt;/i&gt; 52 (3), 470-476.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Van der Merwe, Alwyn, Franco Selleri and Gino Tarozzi (eds.). 1988. &lt;i&gt;Microphysical Reality and Quantum
Formalism: Proceedings of the Conference &amp;lsquo;Microphysical Reality and Quantum Formalism&amp;rsquo; Urbino, Italy,
September 25th-October 3rd, 1985. Vol. 1&lt;/i&gt;. Dordrecht: Kluwer Academic Publishers&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Responding to Edward Feser</title>
      <link>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/post/edwardfeser/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nathanoseroff.github.io/post/edwardfeser/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Edward Feser has a new blog post, &#39;&lt;a href=&#34;https://edwardfeser.blogspot.co.uk/2017/04/the-problem-of-humes-problem-of.html#more&#34;&gt;The Problem of Hume&#39;s Problem of Induction&lt;/a&gt;&#39;. Given my previous response to Eugene Earnshaw, I think it&#39;s appropriate to cover Feser&#39;s two arguments, one which we can call an &lt;i&gt;argument for&amp;nbsp;self-refutation&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;and the second a &lt;i&gt;burden-shifting argument&lt;/i&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
I will begin with the argument for self-refutation, show that it proves too much, then, assuming Feser&#39;s argument that Hume&#39;s Fork is self-refuting, end with the burden-shifting argument. In short, the burden-shifting argument is an argumentative tactic closer to a forced perspective: from a certain angle the argument looks large and impressive (the inductive sceptic is now on the defensive!), but once we are able to move freely, we see from a different angle it is in fact quite small and oddly-shaped in order to give it a certain desirable appearance (the inductive sceptic &lt;i&gt;would be &lt;/i&gt;on the defensive, &lt;i&gt;if&lt;/i&gt; we make the following controversial assumptions).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
1. Hume&#39;s Fork&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Hume&#39;s Fork is as follows--there are two sorts of justifiers for sentences: either a sentence is justified in terms of &#39;relations of ideas&#39; or justified in terms of &#39;matters of fact&#39;. Furthermore, a sentence may either assert the existence of non-abstract entities or not assert the existence of non-abstract entities.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
For example, the sentence, &#39;Triangles have three sides&#39; does not assert the existence of non-abstract entities, for the truth of the sentence is discoverable, in Hume&#39;s words, &#39;without dependence on what is anywhere existent in the universe&#39;, for &#39;though there never were a circle or triangle in nature, the truths, demonstrated by Euclid, would forever retain their certainty and evidence&#39;; it is, as Hume calls it, &#39;intuitively certain&#39;, &amp;nbsp;or &#39;demonstrably&#39; certain: the truth of the sentence is self-evident.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The sentence, &#39;Yield signs are yellow&#39;, however, is a &#39;matter of fact&#39;: it is not &#39;demonstrably certain&#39;, and its negation could hold true, that is, as Hume says, &#39;the contrary of every matter of fact is still possible, because it can never imply a contradiction&#39;; furthermore, it asserts the existence of non-abstract entities, namely yield signs.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Georges Dicker in &lt;i&gt;Hume&#39;s Epistemology and Metaphysics: An Introduction&lt;/i&gt; (1998, 38-40) covers another type of sentence, that is, statements that are &#39;matters of fact&#39; but do not assert the existence of non-abstract entities, such as Hume&#39;s &#39;causal principle&#39;. Whatever principle of induction were presented, it would not assert the existence of non-abstract entities; rather, it would be a bridge principle not unlike a causal principle. For Hume, however, no statement expressing a &#39;matter of fact&#39; is self-evident.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
We now face the first horn of the Fork: is a principle of induction justified in terms of &#39;relations of ideas&#39; in the same way that &lt;i&gt;all bachelors are unmarried&lt;/i&gt; is? A principle of induction does not seem like it falls within the modern taxonomic categories of necessary truths, analytic sentences, or sentences knowable&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;a priori&lt;/i&gt;. Feser acknowledges this difficulty: &#39;it is at least conceivable that bread could fail to nourish us, in a way it is not conceivable that a bachelor could be unmarried&#39;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In more modern parlance, is there some possible world in which &#39;bread nourishes us&#39; is false? Yes, therefore it is not necessary. Is the sentence &#39;bread nourishes us&#39; true by meaning of the constituent terms? No, therefore it is not analytic. Is the sentence knowable without engaging in empirical inquiry? No, therefore it is not &lt;i&gt;a priori&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;i&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;(Note: some defenders of an inductive principle disagree with this assessment, but their defence of this position will not be addressed here)&lt;i&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Consequently, these results exclude a principle of induction being some combination of the categories, such as a synthetic &lt;i&gt;a priori&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;truth or analytic &lt;i&gt;a posteriori &lt;/i&gt;truth; nor could a principle of induction be an &lt;i&gt;a posteriori&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;necessity similar to Saul Kripke&#39;s famous examples, &#39;Hesperus is Phosphorus&#39; or &#39;Water is H?0&#39;.&amp;nbsp;Ergo a principle of induction cannot satisfy the first horn.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Now for the second horn of the Fork: following from Feser, &#39;The proposition that many bachelors go to singles bars is true... because it simply happens to be a contingent empirical fact that many bachelors do this&#39;. Similarly, for a principle of induction to be justified by &#39;matters of fact&#39;, a&amp;nbsp;principle of induction fits more within modern categories of contingent truths, synthetic sentences or sentences knowable &lt;i&gt;a posteriori&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
An inductive principle must be a reliable form of reasoning about &#39;matters of fact&#39;, akin to Hume&#39;s causal principle. For a principle of induction to be accepted as a reliable form of reasoning, there must be grounds for accepting its reliability in the future. The only available grounds are empirical, i.e. its demonstrated reliability in the past; however, this is a form of circular reasoning, justifying the principle of induction &amp;nbsp;by appealing to an inductive inference about its past reliability. Thus a principle of induction cannot satisfy the second horn.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
2. The self-refuting argument&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Feser claims the Fork is &#39;overrated&#39;, for it is &#39;notoriously self-refuting&#39;: the Fork is neither justified in terms of &#39;relations of ideas&#39; nor justified by &#39;matters of fact&#39;. Since the Fork belongs to neither category, it is unjustified. It is, in Feser&#39;s words, &#39;highly problematic at best and demonstrably false at worst&#39;.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The argument for the Fork&#39;s self-refutation is, in Dicker&#39;s words, when phrased against a &lt;i&gt;modernised fork&lt;/i&gt; (MV) (1998, 49), &#39;MV: All knowable propositions are either analytic a priori or synthetic a posteriori. ... Suppose that we ask the following question: is MV &lt;i&gt;itself&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;analytic a priori or synthetic a posteriori?If it is neither, the ... argument is ruined. The upshot is that if MV of Hume&#39;s Fork is true, then it is unknowable!&#39;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Since accepting Hume&#39;s Fork is a necessary premise for Hume&#39;s argument against the possibility of justifying induction and Hume&#39;s Fork is self-refuting, the rationality of inductive inference is (presumably) saved. The dilemma for the inductivist dissipates.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Feser says,&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;tr_bq&#34;&gt;
&#39;Nor can the Humean plausibly salvage the argument by softening Hume&#39;s fork so as to avoid the self-refutation problem. For the softening can take one of three forms. The Humean could liberalize the principle by admitting that there is after all a third category in addition to &#34;relations of ideas&#34; and &#34;matters of fact&#34;; or he could maintain this dichotomy while liberalizing the &#34;relations of ideas&#34; in such a way that Hume&#39;s Fork itself will come out true by virtue of the relations of ideas; or he could maintain the dichotomy while liberalizing the notion of &#34;matters of fact&#34; in such a way that Hume&#39;s Fork will come out true by virtue of matters of fact&#39;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Feser concludes, &#39;Until one of these strategies is actually developed, we don&#39;t really have a Humean &#34;problem of induction&#34;&#39;.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Feser neglects a fourth option, and this neglect can be shown in a (slightly) roundabout way by addressing the following question: &lt;i&gt;does Feser&#39;s argument prove too much&lt;/i&gt;? It may apply equally to any demarcation criteria that do not fall squarely into any domain circumscribed by the criteria, &lt;i&gt;viz&lt;/i&gt;. the same argument may be run against distinctions between more modernised post-Kantian taxonomy: the necessary and contingent, &lt;i&gt;a priori&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;and &lt;i&gt;a posteriori&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;and analytic and synthetic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;2.1 Carnap&#39;s criterion&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Consider for the moment that Feser may find the argument so convincing because he has learned of the analogous charge made against the logical empiricists, with A.J. Ayer in particular. Does this analogy hold? Dicker disagrees (1998, 53-89) with this comparison, since Hume&#39;s definition of &#39;matters of fact&#39; is strictly weaker than syntheticity, but assume that the analogy does hold. Personally, I find this objection against Ayer to be ill-conceived, but in order to give some idea as to why I think the argument for self-refutation does not succeed against the logical empiricists, it is better to look at a stronger case: Rudolf Carnap&#39;s criterion.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
For Carnap, empirically meaningful terms and predicates in a language &lt;i&gt;L&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;are empirically meaningful if they belong to sentences that are either confirmable or disconfirmable (that is, in Carnap&#39;s words, &#39;partially confirmable&#39;); other sentences in &lt;i&gt;L&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;may be analytic (for Carnap, tautologies) or self-contradictory. It is not disputed that Carnap&#39;s criterion of confirmation does not satisfy his own criterion, for it is not confirmable or disconfirmable in &lt;i&gt;L&lt;/i&gt;, nor is it analytic (or, for that matter, obviously self-contradictory) in &lt;i&gt;L&lt;/i&gt;. Is Carnap&#39;s criterion therefore self-refuting on the same grounds as Hume&#39;s Fork?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
One reason to defend Carnap&#39;s criterion from the charge of self-refutation (and, by extension, defend Hume&#39;s Fork from the same charge), is as follows: this form of reasoning is simply too easy to be get at. Any potential bugbear is killed off from a distance--it is trivial to refute Carnap without having to read anything in Carnap&#39;s writings &lt;i&gt;other than his criterion&lt;/i&gt;. It is so easy a child could refute Carnap.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Any argument that appears &lt;i&gt;so&lt;/i&gt; easy as to dismiss Carnap without having read Carnap must, I believe, have been anticipated in some form by Carnap, and would not have escaped the attention of Carnap&#39;s critics. However, this self-refuting argument is not thought within philosophical orthodoxy to have been the knockdown argument for Carnap&#39;s criterion. Therefore we have &lt;i&gt;prima facie &lt;/i&gt;grounds&amp;nbsp;to believe this form of argument just isn&#39;t strong enough on its own to do away with Carnap&#39;s criterion (and, by extension, do away with Hume&#39;s Fork).&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
In fact, if one cares to read anything of Carnap outside his criterion, Carnap has a great deal to say explaining &lt;i&gt;why&lt;/i&gt; he thinks his criterion functions as an appropriate criterion with which to disambiguate our different forms of linguistic discourse (and, implicitly, is not self-refuting).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
First, we must make the distinction between &lt;i&gt;internal&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;questions and &lt;i&gt;external&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;questions for &lt;i&gt;L&lt;/i&gt;, for&amp;nbsp;questions &lt;i&gt;about&lt;/i&gt; linguistic frameworks have both internal and external questions. Internal questions must be raised within and answered within a linguistic framework; external questions are addressed from outside the framework.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
The internal/external distinction can be understood as analogous to a toy example: consider a microbiologist examining different cells on a slide under a microscope. The microbiologist notes that different cells fall into distinct two types, with readily identifiable attributes and behaviours: &lt;i&gt;red blood cells&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;white blood cells&lt;/i&gt;. Questions about the behaviour of the red and white blood cells refer to what occurs on the slide, not what occurs outside the slide; questions about the microbiologist (such as, for example, their criteria for when a blood cell is red or white) refers to what occurs outside the slide, not occurs within the slide.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Questions &lt;i&gt;external to a linguistic framework&lt;/i&gt; can be about the consequences of adopting the framework, but to Carnap it would not make sense to speak of whether answers outside the framework are true or false, or can be judged from &lt;i&gt;within &lt;/i&gt;the framework. It would be, as Carnap called it in the &lt;i&gt;Aufbau&lt;/i&gt; (1929), &#39;mixing of spheres&#39; (&#39;&lt;i&gt;Sphrenvermengung&lt;/i&gt;&#39;), not unlike asking whether the &lt;i&gt;microbiologist&#39;s criterion for red and white blood cells&lt;/i&gt; is a red blood cell or a white blood cell.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Similarly, these sorts of questions that inquire as to whether criteria that demarcate between different linguistic frameworks are &lt;i&gt;true&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;or &lt;i&gt;false&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;(or, in our case, &lt;i&gt;itself&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;subject to its own criteria) &#39;mix the spheres&#39;, or engage in, as Gilbert Ryle calls it, a category-mistake.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Perhaps Feser takes this form of reasoning not to exculpate Hume&#39;s Fork, but condemn Carnap&#39;s criterion as well, and consequently believes that Hume&#39;s Fork &lt;i&gt;and&lt;/i&gt; Carnap&#39;s criterion are self-refuting. However, there are a large number of examples of criteria that are not self-applicable (and therefore self-refuting, by Feser&#39;s lights).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Specifically, we must be careful that Feser&#39;s argument does not result in the dismantling of the traditional borders between analytic and synthetic sentences, between the necessary and contingent, the &lt;i&gt;a priori&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;a posteriori&lt;/i&gt;, and so on, all in an attempt to get at Hume&#39;s Fork.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Consider the following question: is the sentence, &#39;All meaningful sentences are either analytic (true in virtue of a sentence&#39;s linguistic meaning) or synthetic (true in virtue of some correspondence between the linguistic meaning of the sentence and some external fact)&#39; &lt;i&gt;itself&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;analytic or synthetic?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The sentence isn&#39;t analytic, but is it synthetic? This is a bizarre question to ask, since it seems that we must first assume some sort of analytic/synthetic distinction in order to categorise sentences, for any instance of a purported correspondence relation would presuppose the analytic/synthetic distinction. That is, naturally, question-begging. Therefore, it is not synthetic. If it is neither analytic nor synthetic, is the sentence, &#39;All meaningful sentences are analytic or synthetic&#39;, self-refuting on the grounds that by its own lights it is meaningless (but also obviously meaningful)?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
If Feser&#39;s argument for self-refutation is allowed to run its course, the baby is not just thrown out with the bathwater, but also the entirety of the bathroom. However, it is not obvious how Feser&#39;s criticism of the Fork doesn&#39;t dismantle &lt;i&gt;too much&lt;/i&gt;. This companion in guilt argument is, I think, fairly strong, and is not addressed by Feser.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
We are left with a choice: either this fourth option is accepted--we maintain our traditional categories of the analytic/synthetic, necessary/contingent &lt;i&gt;a priori&lt;/i&gt;/&lt;i&gt;a posteriori&lt;/i&gt;, &#39;relations of ideas&#39;/&#39;matters of fact&#39;, and note that a case of apparent self-refutation isn&#39;t &lt;i&gt;sufficient&lt;/i&gt; grounds for abandoning a taxonomic system or criterion--or it is not. Is Feser willing to bite the bullet? I think not. Note that this approach does not &#39;soften&#39; the Fork in the way Feser claims, nor does a principle of induction obviously enter through the window once the door is closed. The inductivist must make the further argument that questions about an inductive principle are external to &lt;i&gt;L&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
3. The burden-shifting argument&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Assume Feser is able to get around this companion in guilt argument. Only Hume&#39;s Fork is genuinely self-refuting and all other examples are not. If so, are there any other possible issues with Feser&#39;s argument? I believe there is, specifically his subtle argument from burden-shifting.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
(&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;N.B.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt; We have contravening evidence that bread is not always nourishing: &lt;i&gt;ergot poisoning &lt;/i&gt;and &lt;i&gt;coeliac disease&lt;/i&gt;. Mentioning the existence of ergot poisoning and coeliac disease is, I think, not an instance of a person&#39;s intellect not attaining &#39;a sufficiently penetrating grasp of the natures of bread and of the body&#39;. But assume that Feser includes suitable &lt;i&gt;ceteris paribus&lt;/i&gt; clauses in whatever inductive principle he accepts to rule out these cases.)&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Feser may object to the premises in Hume&#39;s argument for inductive scepticism. That is uncontested. This is true, naturally, of many arguments: premises are contested. If the premises are contested, all this gets is that there exists philosophical disagreement. An appropriate conclusion to be drawn would be to refrain from belief either way, either for the denial or affirmation of an inductive principle until the dispute has been resolved. &lt;i&gt;But this is tantamount to inductive scepticism&lt;/i&gt;. I hasten to note that inductive scepticism&amp;nbsp;is not the &lt;i&gt;denial&lt;/i&gt; of the possibility of an inductive principle; rather, it is the strictly weaker claim that no inductive principle has yet been provided that surmounts well-known objections, such as Hume&#39;s Fork.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
This disagreement does not get us to the desired conclusion that a principle of inductive inference is on par with necessary truths, &lt;i&gt;pace&lt;/i&gt; Feser&#39;s claim, &#39;Perhaps if we had a complete grasp of the nature of bread and the nature of the human body, we would see that it is not in fact possible for bread to fail to be nourishing to us&#39;. Perhaps, but the consequences are not dire for the inductive sceptic, as Dicker notes (1998, 77-80).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The fact that we may be mistaken about analytic sentences, such as &#39;the sum of the angles a Euclidean triangle add up to 180 degrees&#39;, does not make it obvious that we are similarly mistaken about having failed to identify some presently unknown essential nature of bread, such as the sentence, &#39;bread is &lt;i&gt;essentially&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;nourishing to us&#39;. Is the sentence&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;similar &lt;/i&gt;to&amp;nbsp;an analytic sentence? It isn&#39;t obviously so, especially given the troubles Goodman-like predicates present.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
To throw Feser&#39;s claim of &#39;Perhaps...&#39; back at him, perhaps if we had a complete grasp of the essential nature of bread and the essential nature of the human body, we would see that bread behaves differently after a certain date, or in a different spatio-temporal region. It is, as far as we know, not&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;impossible&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
The mere possibility that a purported synthetic sentence&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;is in fact&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;a suitably hidden analytic sentence is not a sufficient reason to treat the sentence as on par with sentences known to be analytic. Feser must provide an additional reason to believe we can arrive at the hidden nature of bread such that part of its essence is nourishing. It does not appear that such a conclusion can be done by way of justification by &#39;relations of ideas&#39;, for it is not an analytic sentence, nor has it been justified by &#39;matters of fact&#39;, for it would be begging the question. Hence Hume&#39;s Fork survives intact. Feser may posit &#39;That bread will nourish the body could be a necessary truth even if we can know that it is true... only by empirical investigation&#39;, but Feser must do more than posit it to address the inductive sceptic&#39;s arguments.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
3.1 The relevance of internal and external questions&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In short, the two sentences are &lt;i&gt;prima facie&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;too dissimilar. What can explain this apparent dissimilarity? A proposal: their dissimilarity is best described by maintaining Hume&#39;s distinction between &#39;relations of ideas&#39; and &#39;matters of fact&#39;, or by maintaining more recent categories of analytic/synthetic, &lt;i&gt;a priori&lt;/i&gt;/&lt;i&gt;a posteriori&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;or necessary/contingent.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
To use William James&#39; term, we can easily talk about the &lt;i&gt;cash-value&lt;/i&gt; of these categories, and their cash-value is shown by the fact that they help explain the apparent general dissimilarity between types of sentences; Carnap, similarly, would note that these conceptual categories provide an &lt;i&gt;explication&lt;/i&gt; of our intuitive concepts.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
These external questions about apparent distinctions between sentences are answered satisfactorily by adopting these conceptual categories, but to do away with these categories would require articulating some further explanation for their failure and a suitable replacement, or at minimum explain why such an activity would be unnecessary, impossible or undesirable.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
3.2 The attempted burden-shift&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
What Feser has done here is fairly ingenious, but not new in philosophy: it involves the shifting of the burden on to the sceptic to argue for some other unrelated claim, to the effect that paradigmatic sentences justified by &#39;matters of fact&#39; cannot be &lt;i&gt;surreptitiously&lt;/i&gt; justified by &#39;relations of ideas&#39;. If the sceptic cannot present a compelling argument, Feser claims victory.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The problem Feser presents is either intractable or quite difficult, for it is itself a sceptical argument that puts the inductive sceptic on his or her heels. Can we &lt;i&gt;really&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;know that an apparently synthetic sentence is not in fact analytic (or &lt;i&gt;vice versa&lt;/i&gt;)? The inductive sceptic, however, need not reel at Feser&#39;s attempt at burden-shifting; instead, they need only ask for the evidence that sentences like &#39;bread nourishes the body&#39; are suitably similar to &#39;the angles of a Euclidean triangle add up to 180 degrees&#39;. This amounts to saying, as previously, the inductivist must show the inductive sceptic that there is no real &#39;cash-value&#39; to these conceptual categories. Feser&#39;s sceptical reply is benign until he provides the next step in his critique of inductive scepticism.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In sum, while I thank Feser for providing a limpid introduction to Aristotelian-Thomist philosophy, as well as some other interesting and insightful articles, I can only conclude Feser&#39;s argument for self-refutation and burden-shifting argument do not stand up to scrutiny.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
10/4/17&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
